Please take your seat and kindly silence your phones
and feel free to borrow insights outside
for simultaneous interpretation.
Thank you.
Welcome to day two of the review meeting of the ROC Taiwan's FIPS CEDAW report, and we're
And now to begin, over to the chair of the international review committee.
Thank you very much and good morning.
We express to you our appreciation for the cooperation of yesterday, for the hospitality,
and for the high level of engagement of government departments and also the civil society.
We thank you very much, honorable minister, for the courtesies that you've extended to us.
We are grateful.
And today we will proceed as scheduled on the agenda, reviewing articles 10 to 12.
And for that exercise, for that session, I'm going to be calling on colleagues who are leading on those articles to present questions,
and then we will open the floor for responses from government at this point.
So, Professor Niklas, you have the floor.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Madam Chair.
Good morning, everyone.
It is a great honor to be back once again here in Taipei and with the task to review the implementation of the CEDAW Convention.
This time we are conducting the review in a changed global political environment.
We experience a new situation where big states and their leaders do not respect the international rule-based forms of cooperation,
but think that they freely can break the rules and conduct policies by force, threat,
and without respect for the rule and law and the international conventions on human rights.
Finland, my own country, and Taiwan both have the common feature that we have strong neighboring states
that are not so much concerned about human rights and the rule of law principles.
And I think that in such a situation it is extremely important for small democratic countries to maintain a strong commitment to human rights,
which help to create a resilient and inclusive society which can stand united in any crisis situation.
We have been asked by some NGOs what credibility the International Review Committee has and whether we have any kind of accountability
and that we should not make recommendations that go against the public opinion.
I therefore want to remind you all of the fact that universal human rights often may go against public opinion
and that they form basic consistent values.
The whole background for the UN human rights system is the experience of what can happen when the so-called public opinion
have been mobilized to aggression and hate towards different ethnic groups, other religions, nationalities,
especially the experience from the Second World War was behind this human rights system.
We in the Review Committee are independent experts on CEDAW.
Our task is to bring in the genuine and prevailing interpretation of the CEDAW Convention into this debate with the State Party.
This is also the base on which our work can be evaluated and for this we are accountable.
I now want to pose some questions on education where Taiwan has a quite robust system in place.
I only have three points to make about education, Article 10 in the CEDAW Convention.
First, we commend you for having followed the recommendation of the 2022 review by introducing since 2023 gender-related studies at three universities.
Our concern, however, is that the funding for these gender-related studies has been granted for three years.
Our concern is what will happen next and will there be continuation of such funding now when the three years are passing.
If the activities in these programs, if they have been successful, can you inform us about the situation with these university studies, what will happen next?
Second, we commend you for the encouraging of girls in the STEM areas of education with good results.
The technological challenges related to future university teaching are, however, big.
The technology makes the use of online teaching cheap and universities are pressed to include an increasing amount of online studies in the curriculum.
At the same time, AI is bringing and to some extent already has brought about huge changes in the use and creation of knowledge.
These changes are likely also to have gender implications.
Are you planning to study these implications in order to make sure that the new technology will not have negative consequences for equality in the educational system?
My third concern relates to the fact that we are still not convinced that the government is doing enough to facilitate the education of vulnerable groups.
We think about stateless children to migrant workers which are reported to only get elementary education until they get 15.
We think of teenage mothers leaving education and falling outside the educational system.
We think of girls and young women with disabilities still facing many problems and constraints, although there has been an increase in the funding for education for people with disabilities.
Can you tell us something of your plans to further enhance the education of these vulnerable groups of women and girls?
Thank you, Madam Chair.
Thank you very much, Nicholas.
I will now yield the floor to the head of the delegation to provide responses to the three core questions that were raised on Article 10.
Thank you. You have the floor.
Good morning, everyone.
I would like to thank the reviewers for the questions.
I think these three questions are focused on education, so I would first like to delegate to the Ministry of Education to answer comprehensively.
And because there are mentions of high-end research and gender, female-related, we're going to ask NSC to follow up.
And because AI was also mentioned about its gender implication, and we're going to ask Moda to take up this question later on.
Thank you.
This is the Ministry of Education.
We're going to ask the Tertiary Education and Departments.
Hello, this is the Ministry of Education on Higher Education Department.
We supported the three-year funding.
It's not just the three-year.
It's a continuous funding.
For these three universities, we would like to delegate some responsibilities.
For example, campus gender campaign.
We asked one of the universities in Kaohsiung to take up the campaign work.
In addition to research, outreach is also a very important part of their work.
And we continue to provide them funding and resources to these institutes for these research and outreach work.
And for vulnerable children and vulnerable groups, including stateless child children.
Regarding vulnerable children and preschool children and for elementary and middle school,
basically stateless children are based on humanitarian considerations.
We provide them an affordable educator service and provide them schooling services.
These are provided by local governments, and that's for preschool and elementary school and middle school.
Okay, it's not about the elementary school and middle school, but after middle school,
after the K-12, vulnerable groups, stateless child or women with disabilities,
what are their educational resources or protections after K-12?
Any protections provided or any ways for them to overcome their disadvantages?
I don't think you answered this question.
We would like to further follow up with this question regarding vulnerable children.
For high schools, we don't have regulations for the protection of these rights.
We will go back and look into it.
Thank you very much.
Anything else you would like to follow up at the Ministry of Education?
What about STEM?
Do you have anything to follow up on STEM?
So this is the Ministry of Education additional information on STEM on university campuses.
Yes, we do have a pilot program for that promotion.
We provide subsidies to female STEM programs for talent cultivation.
In the past three years, we have subsidized many schools and many teams.
The funding comes from not only government, but also businesses,
and also the program requires collaboration with businesses,
and also supports female researchers and students to commit to the program
to deepen and upholster STEM's friendly environment and support environment.
And then if they do have a higher female percentage in the program,
we would also add additional subsidiary to $1 million.
We are promoting this program.
However, with one program, they cannot drive the entire campus to change their program,
so we hope the program can further expand its scope to the entire environment,
entire school organization.
And about National Science Council, can you proceed to provide additional information?
So this is National Science Council, and like the Ministry of Education just said about STEM,
on university and colleges, faculties and researchers' program proposals,
research program proposals for female professors or pregnant researchers,
we have relevant benefits, which means that there are some supporting programs
so that the female professors don't have to worry about their career development.
So that measures will be incorporated into our subsidiary programs,
and also we have an innovative service platform for entrepreneurs.
The name is TTA.
So for female entrepreneurs, we provide on this platform incentives to encourage innovations.
That's the additional information I have.
Thank you.
Moda, Ministry of Digital Affairs, can you talk about AI's impact on gender?
And this is Moda, and about AI's impact as emerging new technology
would further exacerbate gender bias and discrimination.
And then we established AI-EC, its actual evaluation center,
with the core task to evaluate AI products and systems, accuracy and precision and fairness,
and cybersecurity evaluation.
And about fairness, we include gender equality and equality for people with disabilities.
We want to ensure that AI, while they are providing services,
the answer and the results provided would also be compliant with gender equality values.
Thank you.
It is advised that maybe Ministry of Health and Welfare can also talk about children's daycare
and support for women, and then also additional subsidy and support programs for vulnerable students.
Ministry of Welfare and Health, can you provide further information on that?
Ministry of Health and Welfare, with regard to education,
we follow the rules of Ministry of Education as for benefits provided to vulnerable groups.
We do have programs that would support vulnerable teens and children.
Thank you.
Ministry of Education, I think you do have a program that subsidizes STEM female talents programs
for universities and colleges.
Can you further elaborate on this STEM program, if you do have additional information to offer?
Thank you.
About this, in 2025 we are already providing these programs,
so we have approved around 21 universities and 44 programs.
And then also we are going to build environment that is friendly to diverse, gender diversity.
And also schools need to take proactive role in supporting female researchers and faculty researchers.
So for the female researchers, if they have their program approved and subsidized by us,
and then should this researcher become pregnant, and then they can actually further delay and defer the program,
and then they can return to the workplace.
And then also we provide system design and resource allocation, and also campus culture enhancement.
We want to encourage women and build a system that can really support their career development.
And for the resource allocation, we would like to encourage female students to engage in project studies
and enterprise internship and international exchange programs, and about campus culture.
We also need to create and build a friendly and safe campus culture.
This is something we are working on. Thank you.
Do we have additional information our colleagues would like to offer?
This is Ministry of Education.
I would like to add, because you mentioned about the children of people with disabilities,
we also have these education fee deductions for people eligible, depending on household income,
and then also the severity of the disabilities, and then a different deduction of education fees would be offered,
depending on the level of the disabilities.
Is there anything else in the interest of time?
Now I'm going to give the time back to our review board. Thank you.
Thank you very much. The delegation, I would now...
No, you're okay.
Any other follow-up questions?
Okay. Thank you very much.
We will now proceed to Article 11, and I will still yield the floor to Niklas Braun to take Article 11, please.
Thank you.
Thank you, Madam Chair.
We now turn to Article 11 that deals with employment.
The general impression of the implementation of Article 11 is that progress in Taiwan is slow,
although the achievements regarding sexual harassment in workplaces and sexual assault have to be recognized.
These are important achievements.
Regarding employment, I have four areas of concern which I want to address.
The first concern is the implementation of the principle of equal pay for work of equal value.
First, I note that we do not see that the CEDAW standard which requires equal pay to be paid
not only to equal or for the same work, but also for work of equal value has been implemented.
This means that according to the CEDAW standard, we must be able to compare also different jobs
and assess whether they are of equal value.
And if that is the case, there should also be equal pay.
Is, for instance, the work of a nurse of equal value with the work of a typical male job,
a policeman or a worker in the fire brigade?
These are questions that can be posed in the context of the CEDAW approach,
but with your wording in the legislation, it is questionable whether it applies in these cases.
We also note that the wage gap in Taiwan is very persistent.
The government seems to recognize that increased wage transparency
is one important tool in fighting the pay gap.
But the measures that restrict this transparency only to big listed companies
where the paid amount of capital is more than 10 billion NT dollars is really a very high threshold.
Have you, for instance, reflected on introducing a right for the applicant of a job
to get information about the wages of his or her predecessor?
There is a widespread understanding that some of the wage gap is due to the fact
that women have lower wage demands than men when they enter into a new job.
And a right to information about what wages the predecessor was paid could remedy this problem,
and this is a right which has been introduced in many countries.
The principle of equal pay should also be implemented on the whole labor market,
not only in some segment which seems to be the case in the measures that you have been taking.
My second concern relates to the issue of balancing family, childcare, and work.
Here the recognition that something has to be done seems to be well established and accepted,
and the concern about the low birth rate in Taiwan is common,
and since 2018 you have a plan to remedy this.
We note, however, that the list of measures reported in the answer to the list of issues,
we note that there is a long list of different fragmented measures, and this is, of course, understandable.
But we still lack a vision for how to really solve this problem.
Are you aiming for an affordable, high-quality, universal, and non-profit public childcare service system,
or what is the real model which you have in mind?
Also, are we aiming for a system where fathers are taking a substantial responsibility for parental leave
and is an integrated part of the system? The steps in this direction have been quite slow.
For an outside observer, it seems that the system needs some streamlining in order to avoid excessive fragmentation,
but this is, of course, the modest impression for an outsider observer.
It is very difficult to measure the different individual steps that have been taken.
But I would like to get your views on these more principal issues.
The third area of concern relates to the migrant domestic workers.
We see no progress in the situation of migrant female workers,
and since we know that there are almost 300,000 of those existing in Taiwan, this is not a minor problem.
The problems for these groups have been largely documented and they have been addressed last time,
I think, in the report of the ICCPR and the ICCR,
and with an increased number of second-generation, stateless children, the problems are just increasing.
We also know that the ILO Convention 109 on the situation of domestic workers
gives a good model for how these problems could be handled and solved.
I think that from the point of view of the ILO Convention, this is really a serious issue,
and I really urge the government to try to take action on this.
My fourth concern...
The situation of them still needs improvement in the report
or in the answers to our issues and questions.
The Ministry of Labour reports that they have promulgated the administrative guidance
on reasonable accommodation in the workplace for persons with disabilities,
and these have been effective from July 1st to 2025.
This is very welcome, and there is also further guidance on this issue.
But I remind you that these are recommendations for employers,
but actually, under UN standards, the lack of such accommodation would amount to discrimination.
In your system, it is just a recommendation to do this adjustment.
I understand that if employers don't apply them, there are no consequences.
We also note with interest the national action plan on business and human rights,
which you also present in your answer.
The Ministry of Labour here has proposed an action item on promoting the reference guidelines
for enterprises on the prevention of forced labour.
I think this is very important in a situation where new technology brings about new forms
of exploiting vulnerable groups in the working life.
We have platform work, different forms of digital work.
We have different forms of what in international vocabulary has been called modern slavery,
which is related to forced labour.
We think that this action plan is very important, and this should be taken forward,
and it is also related to the question of migrant domestic female workers,
which are in a situation which is quite equal to those who risk forced labour,
because these people can also be exploited on the private sector,
and this is what you are dealing with here.
So we urge you to go forward with these activities,
and I just want to hear how you are dealing further with these questions,
and how you are dealing with different vulnerable groups on the labour market.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much for raising those intersecting concerns.
I'm sure the delegation would have responses,
and I will turn the floor over to you for your consideration and replies.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Regarding Article 11, the reviewer had four main concerns,
mostly concerning the Ministry of Labour,
so I would like to invite the Ministry of Labour to elaborate on this.
And regarding the first question about equal pay for equal work,
we are going to ask if the FCC can answer this question,
and the Department of Gender Equality will also follow up.
The second question is about family care, child care, and work balance.
In addition to Ministry of Labour, which has already touched on it,
maybe Ministry of Education and Minister of Health and Welfare
can also pick up on the question regarding child care.
And finally, regarding the digital forced labour issue,
MODA can answer this question as well.
And also Ministry of Economic Affairs can take the first and fourth question
at the end.
This is the Ministry of Labour.
This is the first time we are talking.
We are at the Department on Employment Equality.
I would like to thank the reviewers for providing us with these comments and questions.
First of all, about narrowing the wage gap.
We agree equal pay for equal work is about the equal value.
And when we talk about equal work and equal pay,
in order for different enterprises to understand what equal pay for equal work means,
in 2023 we came up with a checklist for our competent authorities
to see if the equal pay for equal work is in line with the definition internationally.
And for all the HR departments to understand the concept of equal pay for equal work,
and we will continue to reinforce this concept with the enterprises in Taiwan.
And further, regarding the transparency of wages,
in addition to it being reflected in our checklist,
we also asked for voluntary disclosement from the enterprises.
Currently, large companies that are listed,
companies that have a volume of net worth over 10 billion new Taiwanese dollars,
they must disclose their gender information and their pay information versus their gender.
And in addition to this self-checklist for equal pay for equal work for business entities,
we understand that it's not just for large corporates, but for smaller enterprises.
The central government is working with the local governments when we are doing our compliance visits.
We also send out this self-checklist for different companies
so that they all understand and have the concept of equal pay for equal work.
And as of June this year, we've issued over 36,000 checklists to these business entities,
so they understand this concept.
And reviewers also talked about family care and work balance, specifically the child care.
We really care about this in addition to reinforcing our measures for child care subsidies to the enterprises
to build child care facilities or building measures in addition to amending the acts.
We currently have a reward measure that is in the Legislative Yuan pending adoption and review.
And regarding the family and work balance,
we understand that the duty of care is not just on one single gender.
So this year we emphasize that dual gender participating in the family care is very important.
And we discussed with CSOs, and they've shared with us that when they are trying to balance family and work,
the care, time, and balance is issue.
So we are moving towards a more flexible value so that different genders can take parental leaves flexibly,
and they can care for family and work at the same time.
Starting from January 1st this year, we have a new parental care policy that is more flexible.
From January to June, we can see over 50% of male have applied for parental leave.
And in the past, men only accounted for one-third of the parental care,
but now we are amending the regulations so that we are formalizing the parental leave
so that we can reinforce the maternity checkup leave and parental leave can be reinforced for the male.
And from currently seven days to 14 days for these maternity checkup leaves,
and for parental leaves for both parents, it's six plus three months now for both parents.
And this is an amendment that's currently being reviewed at the Legislative Yuan.
That's for the family work balance.
And regarding the foreign domestic workers' rights in Taiwan,
after six sessions of listening from CSOs, employers, and families that hire domestic workers,
we have compiled six aspects of the rights and benefits that need to be protected for our foreign domestic workers.
And through our policies and administrative measures and tools,
we are going to put out comprehensive ways, which my colleague will follow up later.
We will spare no measures to protect the rights of foreign domestic workers.
And regarding workers with disabilities, right now we have administrative guidances,
but if the person with disabilities asks for adjustments and the employer says no,
in the past it has constituted discrimination, and according to our Employment Act, it's still a violation.
And we are now in the process of encouraging corporations to actively take measures to adopt,
and that's what we have done so far.
This is also from the Ministry of Labor, the Enterprise Development Office.
Regarding childcare in companies, in addition to public childcare,
we also encourage companies to provide childcare measures and facilities from 2002 to 2026.
On June 26, we have subsidized over 4,700 enterprises,
or 47 counts of business entities to provide childcare services and facilities.
And it's a figure up to 0.4 billion as of June this year.
I would also like to add, this is also from the Ministry of Labor,
we currently have 220,000 foreign domestic workers in Taiwan,
and we will further take inventory of the contracts that we have for them.
We asked CSOs to host seminars and workshops to discuss the implementations
and for the rights protections of the domestic workers.
We provide measures including, before they enter Taiwan, they must participate.
The employers must take part in a seminar before they bring in the foreign migrant worker,
and the migrant worker must also take part in the seminar.
Also at the service station, at the airport, we also have a consultation station.
And once they come into the country, we have a hotline, 1-995.
That's a 24-hour hotline providing bilingual consultation and complaint services.
We also have local government migrant worker consultation service centers
that conduct routine surveys, checkups for violations.
And if migrant workers, they are under labor and wage disputes and they need legal aid,
they can also access this support and service from these local centers,
and they may have maladaptions in terms of languages and communications.
So we also have digital learning trainings to provide the Mandarin training courses.
If they are seriously injured and require assistance,
we have settlement and assistance provided.
And in terms of social resources, we also subsidize local governments
to produce cultural programs that will help them adapt to life in Taiwan
to protect their life pre and post entering Taiwan.
And in terms of forced labor, as our viewer mentioned earlier, Ron,
we have our own guideline for forced labor,
and this was enacted in February this year,
and it's currently launched in various local governments.
And we work with the Ministry of Economic Affairs and a fishery agency
to conduct campaigns, hearings, and we conduct,
we made tools based on ILO 11 indicators regarding forced labor.
And also in terms where it implicates our criminal code and human trafficking law
and Basic Labor Act, we will continue to promote all of this.
The core indicator about forced labor is the detaining of their documents,
and in April this year we have amended our laws, our Employment Act,
which forbids the brokers or employers or anyone from detaining the documents
of these migrant workers under any reason.
And if they violate, there will be penalties.
That's our current amendments and measures right now,
and we will continue to follow up based on the spirit of the conventions.
Any additional information from the Ministry of Labor?
If not, we would like to ask the Financial Advisory Council
to provide additional information.
FSC, please.
FSC, would you like to take the first question?
Equal pay?
Do we have FSC representative here?
So the wage disclosure, FSC, listed companies, disclosure of pay,
do we have FSC representative?
I think I can step in to provide additional numbers.
This is the Ministry of Labor.
So in 2025, according to the results of the evaluation of business governance,
and then the indicator is 4.2 that whether the company has a policy in place
to promote diversified workplace and gender equality policies.
So in 2024, we incorporated company governance disclosure guideline.
So gender equality is factor in.
And then in 2025, the average score of the business,
that average score is 89.78 percent.
So most of the listed companies have already disclosed their workplace
diversified policies and gender equality policies.
So it seems FSC is not here.
So we would like to ask the Department of Gender Equality
to provide additional information on the first question and the second question.
In the Ministry of Education, in the Ministry of Welfare and Health,
please provide your answer to daycare, work and life balance, career balance.
So with regard to workplace gender pay gap,
so Executive Yuan, we did observe a very big challenge.
That is our gender pay gap.
We cannot really gradually, steadily narrow that gap.
Department of Gender Equality conducted analysis,
and also we refer international frameworks.
So that gender pay gap do come with a lot of structural factors.
And then the result is that inequality of gender pay.
We don't have awareness of gender equality in workplace.
And then also the workplace is not friendly enough to women.
And also there are these like promotion ceilings vertically and horizontally.
And also there are different barriers between different industries.
And then that comes with a very big gender pay gap variance between different industries.
So we actually saw the gender pay gap inequality is the result of many folds of factors.
So we need to take a comprehensive and inter-administrative collaboration.
Therefore, we need to establish a gender-friendly workplace
and also empowering women's economic capability.
That is an issue for many ministries.
So we have strategies, for example, to narrow the horizontal and also the vertical gender segregation.
So we have programs to cultivate STEM female talents.
And then also National Science Council, Ministry of Education, and MODA would provide empower programs.
And also there are gender equality awareness workshops.
And then also we coach our listed companies to follow GRI to disclose their gender equality information.
And also we ask them to also cultivate prospects and potential female talents.
And also we want to cultivate a friendly workplace.
And then also vertically for the women, they would not hit a promotion ceiling.
And when it comes to gender pay gap in industries, we actually see there is a big gender pay gap when we compare different industries.
Therefore, we ask competent authorities to identify, for example, the manufacturing industry for electronic appliances.
These industries, they need, the competent authority of these industries need to provide measures to address this issue
and also provide further protection, advancement of women's workplace rights.
And also they need by stage aspects to disclose that information.
And then the pay gap data collection allows us to monitor the pay gap development over the years
as a basis for us to look into the issue so we can narrow the pay gap.
And also that data collection can help us to develop policy for equal pay promotion.
That is the work we have been doing here.
And Department of Gender Equality, have you covered all the grounds you want to cover?
Yes. Ministry of Welfare and Health and on daycare, maybe Ministry of Education can also provide further information on that.
MOEA, can you also chip in?
And MODA, you can also provide the digital forced labor issue as a Ministry of Health and Welfare.
Before I talk about daycare, so I would like to thank all the members of IRC for staying,
paying close attention to the low birth rate issue here in Taiwan.
In 2018, Executive Yuan has asked all ministries to pull resources together to address the issue.
So a daycare service is a critical element in that to help families strike a balance in parental obligations and job career balance.
So our goal is to establish public daycare services.
From 2021 to 2024, that public daycare services has grown by 53 percent.
And then also the daycare of children under two, that percentage has reached 56 percent.
And then also we want to publicize daycare services.
It takes time. We cannot do that overnight.
Therefore, at the same time, we utilize the quality private daycare centers and also at home daycare personnel to establish on par public daycare services.
As long as they are compliant with government standards, they can sign contracts with the government.
So the government can also leverage private resources to allow parents to enjoy these affordable daycare services with all these measures in place.
And then these child care daycare adoption rate for under two years old children has already grown to 56 percent.
And then when governments trying to advance this balance between parental obligation and job and work,
we also need to have supportive measures that drive for a friendly workplace.
And then from 2018 to 2025, and then we have already increased our budget to 120 billion.
And the Ministry of Education here at the Ministry of Education.
So additional information for preschool education and then like the Ministry of Education,
as our Ministry of Health and Welfare, we actually pull resources together across 12 ministries.
And then for these preschooler daycare that for year age two to five preschoolers,
we also expanded the supply of affordable daycare services to lessen our parents burden.
So for the publication of daycare services from 2018 as of 2026,
we have already increased the number to 90,000 availability.
And then so because for that supply, when it's deployment and we do have time limitation.
So we are also working together with private kindergartens.
So they are on par to the public funded kindergartens.
So we also offer 253,000 seats in this preschool kindergartens.
So we can see that preschoolers under two that they actually enter into the kindergarten and the number grow significantly.
So we can actually see that number has grown from 16% to 64%.
And we also see that growth of children entering into kindergarten between two to five grow to 86%.
And to promote comprehensive daycare.
And then for those parents who send their children to private kindergartens,
we also provide additional benefits and allowances to lessen their financial burden.
And also to help them to strike a balance between family and career.
That in 2020, for these competent authorities,
we coach them to set up daycare support centers for parents.
So we have altogether 165 sites like this.
We provide up to 9,500 vacancies.
So all the government employees can also work with a sense of ease.
Thank you.
We would like to invite Ministry of Economic Affairs to answer the first and fourth question.
Here we are at the SME Innovation Startup Office
regarding the work and childcare balance and the workplace benefits and work balance.
First of all is we incentivize them through rewards and dedicated rewards
to encourage enterprises to implement work and childcare balance
and the flexible rights of the laborers.
For example, we have the national level indicative awards
and other innovative startups and various awards.
We have about a weighting of 10 to 15 percent that's placed on building a work-friendly workplace
and gender-balanced workplace.
And work-life balance, work-family balance is a very important indicator.
From 2021 to 2024, there were 246 companies that were awarded.
And in work-family-friendly and balanced award that was established in 2023
to award companies that provide flexible working hours and family-friendly workplace.
And as of 2024, we have selected 13 friendly companies as role models for others to learn from.
So over these four years, we've noticed that most of the companies that were awarded,
about 80 percent of them, they demonstrated they have excellent performances
in terms of allowances for substantial allowance for childcare and flexible working hours
and flexible working modes, for example, working from home and including pick-up children.
They're given flexible hours, and if they raise children less than three years,
they can lessen one hour of their working hour per day.
These measures are substantially provided by the enterprises to the employees.
And in terms of narrowing the wage gap, we encourage enterprises to raise the salary for their workers.
And in 2024 August, we amended our SME Development Act in Article 36
when you are willing to raise the salary of the lower-level workers.
And you can effectively raise your profitability from 100 percent to 130 percent.
And that's a very good incentive to narrowing the wage gap and moda here regarding the digital forced labor.
The core is about the discipline of enterprises and their self-protection.
As mentioned by Ministry of Labor earlier on,
there is a guideline launched by the Ministry of Labor regarding forced labor prevention.
And even though digital tools can be used by employers to require of our workers,
but these digital tools are used for work assistance, not for forced labor.
We will continue to encourage the enterprises not to do so and to do outreach.
So these are the answers we have provided so far.
Any agencies or departments would like to follow up?
Ministry of Health and Welfare Long-Term Care Department,
we would like to follow up on the foreign domestic workers employed in Taiwan
taking care of disabled elders or persons with disabilities at home in our long-term care system.
They are eligible for respite services as well.
So we also provide budgets for short-term care.
Last year, the domestic workers employed at home to care for people with disabilities,
about 50% of these families applied for respite care,
and the total usage was 2.6 million times,
and over 2.6 million people that have used these services,
and we've allocated over 1.5 billion in budget.
This is additional information provided for our reviewers.
Any follow-up?
At NSC here, we would like to add everybody mentioned equal pay for equal work at workplaces,
and the three science parks under our jurisdiction, we currently have over 350,000 employees.
They make up for 20% of our GDP, so we care very much about workplace equality,
and we have been holding awards for outstanding companies for over 10 years in 2024 in our evaluation indicators.
We included the ratio of the increase of female management.
It's a very important evaluation because if we care about equal pay for equal work,
and if we're not able to increase the rate of female management, it won't be as effective.
In the interest of time, we now give the floor back to our reviewers.
Thank you very much for your very comprehensive answers to my questions.
I want one issue to be clarified, because when we yesterday discussed the issue of introducing a comprehensive act on discrimination,
and then we understood that one of the problems with the preparation of the act was how to deal with disabled people with disabilities,
and the demand that there should be adjustments for these people.
So now I understood that actually in the present legislation on employment and discrimination,
there already is regarding employment a requirement that the employer should do these reasonable workplace adjustments,
otherwise it is discrimination. That's how I understood it.
And then my question is, are there any cases where employers have been punished for having not done these adjustments?
Is this also a more theoretical issue, or is it working also in practice? Thank you very much.
Thank you. I also have a question after you.
Thank you. Listening to the explanation provided by the Ministry of Labor,
I consistently heard equal pay for equal work.
And the question was whether you apply the concept of equal pay for work of equal value.
And when you explain to the companies the concept, do you also include this issue?
It's easy that you try to guarantee equal pay for the same work for female teachers, male teachers, female judges, male judges.
It's easy to understand, and nobody should be discriminated.
But what he raised is equal pay for work of equal value when the work is completely different,
but you have to estimate what kind of responsibility, what level of skill is needed.
So it might be completely different work, but might have same value.
So it needs government's effort to establish that kind of comparison, which work has the same value.
And we need to give equal pay for work of equal value.
That's what the convention means.
So I want to ask you whether when you understand this concept, do you have this understanding of equal pay for work of equal value?
That would be my question.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I think in addition to that, there's an overarching question of computation.
Have you taken the effort to calculate the unpaid care work economy in Taiwan?
Because until you have that baseline and you know the size of your unpaid care work,
then valuing work in different sectors becomes not completely objective.
And your national accounting system is missing in certain areas because work that is unpaid is not integrated into your economic planning.
And so the question is, in determining this equal work of equal value,
do you have a baseline that says in the formal, in the informal sector, this is the level of unpaid care,
this is the level of paid care so that the size of your labor market and your economy is clear?
Because this has also implications for the gender tax gap and which impacts also on gender pension gaps.
So if you are not looking at it as a spectrum, you know, as a continuum,
and you just start by saying, oh, yes, we have two, a man and a woman working, they're spending eight hours a day,
eight hours of cleaning and washing and sweeping may not be the same as eight hours of a telephone receptionist.
So valuing the work also means you have to expand your understanding of the care economy,
the formal economy, the enterprise economy, the market economy.
All of those make up your system.
So do you have that baseline is a question that I would like to put to the government because you are undertaking reforms,
but against what background?
Because if you don't have this data, then it's difficult to be able to assess how your progress is making an impact and closing gender gaps.
And so I would like to turn to the delegation maybe for quick answers because we still have Article 12,
where you have it and where you don't.
And we thank you for the very extensive responses that we've received this morning.
Thank you very much.
OK.
The majority of these questions still fall under the Ministry of Labor,
especially about the calculation about equal work, equal pay, and for equal value and equal pay.
And the unpaid work issue, we would like the Ministry of Labor to quickly answer this question.
Regarding the question proposed, as we explained earlier on,
for business entities when they are promoting the right concept of equal work for equal pay,
we have a self-checklist and we have revised the checklist every year.
Two years before, we tell the business entities, you need to understand the job descriptions of each role,
not just looking at the same title, same job, and then you have the same pay.
It's not the same thing.
So we are taking steps to guide the business entities to understand, first of all,
understand their job descriptions, understand the values of these jobs, and to look at the standards of their pay.
And for all employees, when the employers are understanding the job description,
yes, we did not differentiate the paid and unpaid ratio.
But overall, after the first step, they understand the job descriptions,
then they can look at the pay that they provide for these jobs,
their differences in different gender or gender orientations.
That's the guidance right now.
And the next question, we also like to ask the Ministry of Labor to take about the penalty.
Basically, for the reasonable accommodation for disabled people, we do have a guideline.
In practice, I think our question in concern is actually the direct violation of Employment Service Act.
So we do have, in the past two years, actual cases in court that citation
because the employer refused to make reasonable accommodation for persons with disabilities.
In the ruling, the judge made it very clear it's a violation of the Fair Employment Act.
So the employee was employed, the contract was terminated.
So it was actually a lawsuit about employment.
So that termination of employment contracts is a violation against law.
Any additional information? If not, we're going to give the floor back to IRC.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Honorable Minister.
I want to appreciate the responses that you gave.
I was hoping that we would hear about a national standard on valuation of work
rather than leaving it to the discretion of individual companies.
And so in that area, I'm not sure that the expectation on this side of the room was met.
I also did not get any direct response to your calculation of your unpaid care economy.
The size of it and how it relates to both the public and the private sector.
But because we are moving on to Article 12, I would urge the head of delegation
to provide those answers along with the answers from yesterday
and to indicate when we would receive those answers in writing short, crisp,
so that it can help us in considering the recommendations to the government.
Thank you.
Thank you, Madam Chair.
Then we can...
Thank you, Madam Chair. I would like to offer additional information.
Actually, when it comes to equal pay for equal work or equal pay for equal value,
we know that indeed we are more focusing on these equal pay.
And it's the calculation of it is actually calculated on the basis of hourly pay.
So we are not yet there to actually doing an evaluation of equal pay for equal value.
Therefore, indeed, when it comes to data collection and computation,
we haven't established a system for that.
So for equal pay for equal value, because it will involve not only public sector,
it will involve this immense private sector.
So we need to do this step by step.
We need to see first have transparency of wages before we move on to the evaluation of the value.
But definitely that will be one direction we are working toward to.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Do you still have a response?
No. Thank you.
Now I will yield the floor to Professor Leti to take article 12.
Thank you. You have the floor.
Thank you, Madam Chair.
At first, I want to congratulate you on the quality of your health service system.
However, I have some specific questions about women's health.
The State Party reports that the contraceptive prevalence rate is 67 percent
and provides data on maternal mortality and health indicators.
Please provide information on access to sexual and reproductive health services,
including disparities affecting marginalized women and regional disparities.
Please indicate whether requirements such as esposal consent in case of married women
or parental consent in case of adolescents remain as requirements for access to abortions.
In vitro fertilization is permitted only for heterosexual couples.
What are the reasons for excluding single women or married lesbian women?
Please provide information on measures taken to ensure accessible and inclusive health care
for women with disabilities, including the availability of adaptive services
such as counseling and disability-friendly facilities.
Are there data of obstetric violence in hospitals, especially against marginalized women?
Please indicate how women, including women's organizations,
are consulted in the development of health policies, particularly those related to reproductive rights.
Thank you.
Thank you, Chair.
Thank you very much. You have the floor, Minister.
Thank you.
So I think these three questions are questions that should be taken by Ministry of Health and Welfare.
So Ministry of Health and Welfare for the National Health Agency would like to first take this question.
So thank you very much for these questions.
So for the questions for reproductive health-related services provided,
so for different groups, including teenagers and parents and also the educators and health care providers,
we did develop different teaching materials and health education materials for these different groups,
and we also have a copy and a version for disabled persons,
and then that information will be provided on our Health Nine-Nine official website.
We also have dedicated sections on websites providing information to different groups and communities.
That is the first answer.
And then when it comes to the Genetic Health Act, when it comes to the abortion option,
that the spousal consent is required that, indeed, when it comes to draft,
we have already deleted that provision for the spousal consent.
And in the deliberation process, we also would invite women's rights advocacy group to join the public hearing,
and then we are going to follow the regulation amendment procedures to give announcements beforehand,
and we will collect and consult with the public.
So that is the information we have here for the second question.
And for the Genetic Health Act, it's still in the process of drafting and revision,
and then there are conflicting views on that.
So our government agency will continue to talk to women's rights group and also religious groups and parents groups.
They have different arguments, and we will continue to collect their opinions for the regulatory amendment work.
So that are the two answers to the first two questions.
With regard to health, maybe the medical affairs department agency can answer the question.
So the medical affairs from issue of health and welfare.
So I would like to provide three pieces of information here.
First, now in Taiwan, the coverage of national health insurance here in Taiwan is as high as 99.6 percent.
Our public do enjoy quality accessibility to medical care.
And for the medical facilities, the outpatient clinics, their accessibility environment for hospitals,
we do, they have to comply with this accessibility law.
And now for outpatient clinics, there are no specific requirements for outpatient clinics for accessible facilities.
However, we have incentive programs to help these outpatient clinics to build accessible environment.
And every year we have 15 million of budget to help these outpatient to build accessible and friendly environments.
And then we have around more than 2,000 outpatient clinics have already been subsidized so they can build an accessible and friendly environment.
That's additional information we have.
With regard to issue of health, any additional information?
I think the national health agency, so the mortality rate of pregnant women and also the accessibility of reproductive health.
And then I think for the mortality rate, to our statistics, the numbers, I think it's already stated in the report.
And then for the mortality rate, the maternal mortality rate has been gradually reducing.
And it's already down to a level that is on par with international standards.
And when it comes to medical services, especially accessibility to relevant information,
so the information of medical accessibilities are all offered to these relevant groups.
So, and also the medical fair office also said that it's actually quite convenient for our citizens to seek medical help in Taiwan.
So here I would like to address the questions I have not yet answered.
In terms of vulnerable women, minority group women, when it comes to their accessibility to gynecologists or OBGYN,
are they suffering any harassment or violence, and then do you have any preventive measures for that?
And then also for Ministry of Education, there is actually a manual for disabled women that is published by Ministry of Education.
So maybe you can talk more about that, but we would like to ask Ministry of Health to go first.
So this is a protective service office.
So for medical facilities and OBGYN clinics, should there be sexual harassment issues?
So the Sexual Harassment Prevention Act, basically for medical facilities,
there are liabilities for the operators of these patient clinics and hospital facilities.
So they have to put in place the remediation and measures to prevent sexual harassment.
And in and during, there are supportive measures.
And if they fail to comply to these policies, there are also penalties for them.
So that is the preventive measures for sexual harassment prevention.
So this manual, resource manual for disabled women, for different age groups of women.
So we have manual for 0 to 18 years old disabled women.
And we are now collecting data of the actual application of this manual at different levels of education facilities.
And then we are going to follow up on that and continue to update the manual accordingly.
And any other agencies or government ministries would like to respond to this health-related issue?
If not, now I'm going to give time back to IRC.
So additional information.
Personally, at a quarter to 11, I have to leave first because I have to attend a meeting.
So if we haven't finished by then, now I'm going to ask Director General Lin to take over for moderating the answering process.
Thank you very much, Head of Dedication.
I'm sure we're making steady progress and we should be able to finish.
I'm coming back to this side of the room for follow-up questions.
And I'm sure that you have the floor later for, you have no follow-up questions?
So for Article 12, I believe that we do not have any other follow-up questions.
But I would like to place a reminder on the table for the questions that yesterday we were told we would receive answers today.
And I think there was one other question this morning about unpaid care work that we said we will get in writing.
And just a reminder that I know the Head of Dedication may be stepping out and handing over to a colleague that we want assurance to know when we would receive those from the Minister.
So that because we were needed in the preparation of the report.
And I yield that to you before we close the session and adjourn for the break.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Yesterday it was mainly the MOI that needs to provide the answer in written form.
And this morning we talked about unpaid care and also the national evaluation of and calculation standard for equal pay for equal work and equal value.
And I think the Ministry of Labor can coordinate this.
If we have any answers to follow up, we should, we require everyone to provide your written form, written answer this afternoon, including the question proposed today.
So both written answers from yesterday and today must be provided by this afternoon.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
And I'm sure I hand over back to you.
And thank you for a very interactive morning session for the article.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
And now we take a 15-minute break and we'll be back by 1047.
We'll be back by 1047.
Thank you very much for your participation.
This is the meeting of the committee and the NGO.
Thank you again for your participation.
At the same time, I would like to remind you that if you don't want to submit additional information, please prepare seven English versions and two Chinese versions before the end of today's meeting at 6.30.
Please help us submit the report outside the venue.
If you want to submit additional information, please prepare seven English versions and two Chinese versions before the end of today's meeting at 6.30.
Thank you.
At the beginning of the meeting, please put your hands on the door.
Yes.
Okay, welcome back.
And we're now in another session with the NGOs.
Next is another meeting with the committee and non-governmental organizations.
We will focus on Article 10 to 12.
We're going to focus on Article 10 to 12.
Members, we will speak for one minute each time.
In each round, we will speak to the NGOs who haven't spoken yet.
Thank you.
Okay, and now back to the chair to open this session for us.
Thank you very much and good morning.
You are welcome to day two of the review, the fifth review, CEDAW review process.
And as usual, we will be taking NGO additional inputs to presentations on Articles 10, 11, and 12.
And now I'd like to open the floor for Article 10.
And I urge you to please focus your input contributions to Article 10 to make it easy for us to distill the recommendations.
Otherwise, it becomes difficult.
And so for those who are taking the floor, I'm sure you will help with the time management as has been the practice.
So it's open now for inputs to Article 10.
Thank you.
Anyone who would like to raise comments on Article 10?
None from Roll 1?
Maybe we can start from Roll 2.
Thank you.
So on behalf of the Equality of Life Rights Association, so on Article 10 to 11,
so you're not really responding to the actual equality of women.
Many of the women had to quit their jobs to take care of family and they losing their career opportunity due to rearing their children.
So there are no results.
There are only measures.
This is not about setting how much budget aside.
It's truly about how women can have equal access to develop opportunities.
We asked the government to provide actual results, including information on women's pay gap and then the promotional pay gap.
Also, we want to see the actual improvement, not only beautiful numbers.
And also, I think sustainability is the fashion here for healthy advancement for women's rights.
And women, if their status can be improved, that will definitely increase family happiness in the society and reducing social issues.
I think in third roll, we can start from here.
Thank you.
Good morning.
This is the Taiwan Sexual Education Association.
And we have been doing this for many years, and we are very welcome on campuses across Taiwan.
And we also provide only sexuality education in Taiwan.
This is something that the government should take pride in.
However, overnight, because the gender equality advocacy groups are in one line, we are being lined and attacked as the opposition to as a party in a position to comprehensive gender education.
So they are making these attacks on us due to their ideology.
However, sexuality education is very important.
We need to do it right to protect our teenage children.
For example, we have this serious issues in terms of STT transmission on campus.
And then these gender equality education organizations in Taiwan, they don't have past experiences and they're only sourcing from these online influencers information.
Therefore, we need to urge the government to take into account the importance of proper sexuality education.
Please stop these non-professional organizations to step into campus.
And also, the Ministry of Education should take a neutral grant to serve as...
Next one.
This is Taiwan Mothers Shield Alliance.
We have the textbook in Taiwan to actually teaching the children to set the healthy boundaries, but they also have this additional manual.
So on page 107, there is a teaching program here.
There is a song.
The boy said, can I just put my penis in?
Your husband has not come back.
So I have these hearts racing.
And the girl said in this lyrics that, yes, you can come in for a little bit.
So this is additional information and material for these teaching material.
Why?
Because on the fourth seat or in the past two covenants review, you have been promoting comprehensive gender education.
Is this what you're aiming for?
Is this your ideal gender equality education?
If we don't have these preventive measures put in place, it's going to harm our next generation.
Thank you.
The one next to you, this is the Taiwan Parents Association for Children's Rights.
According to Article 10, equal access to education rights.
And then also we have these article 19 and article 10 of the Gender Equality Education Act.
We had these comprehensive guidelines for these comprehensive gender sexuality education.
And then also many articles emphasizing the importance of sexuality and sex.
And they're not really teaching a lot of sexual health.
And for example, there are kind of improper lyrics that are quoted in the manuals.
And also asking boys and girls in the classroom to talk about penises.
And then this is the so-called comprehensive sexual education.
This is actually blindly transplanting the so-called event country's ideologies.
And then these competent authorities in action in a standing guard.
And then we think we need to take a review of the implementation of article 10.
And then also it's actually heavily impacting the sexual health of children.
And we are not seeing the women's health improved.
And then we are actually seeing these sexual transmitted diseases for women.
Please focus on article 10.
Thank you.
So this is the Taiwan Equality Education Association.
So even the Ministry of Education has been promoting the comprehensive sexual education.
However, it's just a supplemented manual.
So they haven't taken full inventory of the entire curriculum.
So it's actually a big disparity between the curriculum and also the manual.
And then also the spirits of comprehensive sexual education.
And also a lot of these organizations are taking the content out of the context and then launch their attack.
And they only focus on chastity, these kind of ABC kind of sex education.
They are negatively emphasizing the risk of sex.
So they are again, again, stigmatizing sex.
Because we want the government to amend their curriculum to complement and
also comprehensively review their curriculum for improvement.
Thank you.
This is the Awakening Foundation.
We suggest that the reviewers can look at the overall resource allocation imbalance and the lack of effective evaluation.
The problem of sexual education in Taiwan is because since the Gender Equality Education Act was enacted 20 years ago,
in order to reinforce the education,
we don't have the right environment and the resources for the gender equality events investigation in the campus.
But we don't have the relevant and corresponding teaching methods and teaching materials and the teacher's training.
So we don't have the corresponding resources invested.
So gender equality education so far, is it really substantially equal?
And do we have the fundamental research to really look at the systematic changes and the overall changes of students' mentality and trends?
So we are unable to substantially adjust accordingly.
Thank you.
The Ministry of Education has encouraged female to invest in STEM regions,
but for female students with disabilities are actually unable to choose STEM courses.
For example, laboratories need to make accommodations, but these hardware are not accommodated for disabilities.
The Ministry of Education should make regulations for reasonable accommodations to assist these students with disabilities.
Thank you.
I would like to talk about the transitional justice encompassing the female perspective,
because when women are talking about their transitional justice and trauma, they are talking about this history.
They are not just talking about systematic violation, but they are also part of the victims and sexual assault.
But the society rarely focuses on their narrations.
So when we are searching for truth and searching for the significance of the Taiwan history,
when Ministry of Culture are outsourcing these works,
are they including the female perspective, women's perspective in transitional justice?
And I think that's a very important issue in all of our contracted cases.
We shouldn't just make males heroes and disregard the special experiences of women.
We are from the Parent Protect Women and Children Association.
We believe that the government continues to disregard the realistic environment of children and women.
The government says in number 30 that the curriculum is diverse,
but there are sexual innuendo lyrics that are used in the courses.
We can see in our teaching materials and all of these lyrics that are quoted with sexual innuendo,
these should not be offered for download on school websites by minors.
This turns the hotline.
Right now the Sexual Equality Education Act is implemented in Taiwan.
So every semester in schools there are four hours of sexual equality courses,
but the government have never really established a comprehensive evaluation mechanism.
So in reality the teachers reflect that gender equality education focuses more on gender-based violence,
and LGBTQ diverse gender education and sexual education are not focused on.
So I think we encourage the government to focus on different themes so that they can really be implemented in the schools.
Regarding Article 10, are there any other NGOs that would like to respond?
Thank you very much.
I believe we will now proceed to Article 11,
and I would urge that we give the floor to those who haven't taken the floor,
to have the opportunity to engage for this next round of Article 11, which is on employment.
The floor is open.
Thank you.
Even though same-sex marriage has been legalized in Taiwan for seven years,
it doesn't mean that discrimination at workplace has disappeared.
In reality, in practice we notice that there are LGBTQ diverse gendered employees who are afraid to take marital leave or parental leave,
and transgenders, because it's difficult for them to change their sex on their IDs, it's very difficult.
So when they are looking for employment, they face a lot of unreasonable barriers and discriminations,
even though these discriminations can be dealt by our law, but penalizing discrimination is the last resort.
I think at root we should educate the public and the employees.
The government should reinforce labor inspection and education,
and they should have the responsibility to understand diverse genders.
Thank you very much.
I would like to follow up.
I am the Taiwan Alliance to Promote Civil Partnership Rights.
Transgender employment in Taiwan is very difficult.
The main barrier comes from it's very difficult for them to change their sex.
So their sex and their gender, legal gender, and their own psychological gender is very different.
Gender identification is very different.
So there are serious discriminations at work.
For example, transgender women are asked to wear male attire to work by the employer,
and I think that's gender discrimination.
Two years ago, the Ministry of Labor expanded the sexual harassment surveyor training courses
and included transgender cases, and I've personally taken these courses many times,
and they are all against these cases and even have wrong evaluations of transgenders.
So we think to prevent secondary discrimination,
the personnel should have more understanding of transgenders in their trainings.
Thank you.
I'm talking on behalf of the Taipei Twin Alliance Association,
Taipei Twin Associations, and General Education Foundation.
Mental health at work is very important,
but there isn't enough training provided for these trainings,
and we can see in all of these trainings we've rarely talked about twins.
Twins have contributed so much to the declining birthrate in Taiwan,
but the mothers are facing domestic violence issues because of raising twins or multiple births,
and they would like to have longer parental leaves because they have two or more children.
And in these family statistics, we don't see twins or multiple births.
So whether it's people seeking care or the intensity of care, these are not seen.
Thank you.
The Taipei Bar Association, in the disparity of gender, racial, and police environment,
we can see there is still an unfriendly environment for sexual harassment complaints,
and there are no gender equality committee established internally.
We see female police being relocated because they have bad performances.
The police are not eligible to the labor workplace survey,
and when the CSOs engage them, we find that these female police are worried about retaliation,
so they don't reflect as much.
We would now like to invite more CSOs, NGOs.
Thank you.
This is the Covenant's Watch.
Refusing to provide reasonable accommodation is discrimination.
In our Anti-Discrimination Act, it constitutes discrimination, but it's an act that has not been adopted.
In our Employment Act, it forbids discrimination, but there is no definition about discrimination.
When it was revised in 2025, reasonable adjustment is a new concept in Taiwan,
so they refuse to state that unable to provide reasonable accommodation means discrimination.
This is a citation of the 2014 CPRD Enactment Act,
and we encourage the reviewers to encourage the government to state that reasonable accommodation is required,
and that it constitutes discrimination if not provided.
Article 11 focuses on female work and non-official and non-formal work and responsibility.
Sex workers are where women should be seen.
Sex workers are eliminated from the legal labor system,
even though they have the national pension and health insurance,
but they don't have the labor identity and they are not allowed to labor pension or parental leave,
and they are often stigmatized from applying for various social subsidies.
We hope the reviewers can encourage the government to be the first to include sex workers,
and especially women and diverse genders into the non-official economic and vulnerable group, women group,
and secondly is to legalize the stigmatization penalty.
We are from the Disability Association in Taiwan for Independent Living in Taiwan.
We know that the government has a lot of policies by the Ministry of Labor,
but they lack the protection for women with disability.
For example, the subsidy for child care at workplace,
but it doesn't accommodate for people with disabilities, so their children are not supported,
and the Ministry of Health and Welfare, when they are looking at the female workforce support,
they are not supporting the women with disabilities in terms of their personal assistance or domestic assistance,
and we should have a clear definition about reasonable accommodation
and there should be a reasonable remedy system.
Let's give the floor to colleagues and partners who haven't made comments yet, please.
Awakening Foundation, making comments for the first time today.
We talk about these public daycare services.
Yes, indeed, the government made significant progress.
We want to point out that daycare service for preschoolers under age two,
that we still face this huge disparity between rural and urban areas.
We don't have a lot of services available in rural area.
Probably we need to rely more on the public services rather than on the market supply,
so we would like to draw your attention to that because in Taiwan we are a super aging society already,
and the women as the main caretaker in the family, they are facing a huge burden,
and then now in the future the women of Taiwan is going to face this huge obstacle for their career development
because after their mid-age that they had to disrupt their career development due to the domestic care needs.
We have observed a lot of women, they have to go home and take care of their elders,
and then they actually have this early retirement that is going to affect the pension they get on annual basis,
and they're going to put them in the risk of later years' poverty.
Therefore, we would like to draw your attention to gender-friendly measures for long-term care,
for example, like subsidies for allowance or these long-term care relief so that we can strike a balance.
Thank you very much.
Regarding Article 11, is it okay that we open the floor to the NGOs that have talked already for Article 11?
Or we move on to...
Okay, now we are going to move on to Article 11, any of the NGOs.
This one, these partners here.
So again, second, making comments, the Taiwan Modern Shield Alliance about the daycare.
The government is really committed to providing daycare services, but we actually have to see.
We do have a good supply.
However, the quality, we see a big disparity.
For example, the teachers, their quality sometimes is quite concerning.
So that is one area to attention to.
And also the daycare policies encourage them to actually send their kids to daycare services.
And for mothers, they don't receive a lot of subsidies for them who are willing to take care of their kids at home.
So this is discrimination against motherhood.
Thank you.
So these alliance for disabled people in Taiwan.
So about the reasonable accommodation, I would like to offer additional information.
According to the Disabled People Protection Act, it's still deliberating in Legislative Yuan about reasonable accommodation,
whether it's a discrimination definition.
So we see that both two parties want to see that the rejection to make reasonable accommodation constitute discrimination,
and there should be penalties.
However, the authoritative rent, so competent authorities still refuse to adopt that,
and they want to, they are not really thinking about how to really promote the practices in business and private sector
and for the disabled women, especially the Category 1 mentally disabled women.
And when it comes to their employment participation, they are only half of the normal women's participation.
And then in terms of the policy change, they are not factoring into the past research guidelines.
The government failed to do so.
Any other additional information?
Taiwan Hotline Association, second time making comments for transgender people in Taiwan in career workplace.
A lot of trans people face great difficulties in seeking employment,
and the Hotline Association did a transgender people census workplace experience,
and then we saw like 40 percent of these transgender people, they have to go into the closet,
and also more than 40 percent of them have to go into the closet.
And so that is a very high percentage.
And also that for another part, and then if they have difficulty in finding employment,
and then they cannot save enough money for their gender marker change.
So that is actually very difficult for their daily life,
because in Taiwan so far, because it is required to go through a surgery for gender marker change.
So they also face the difficulty of not economic difficulty and also big enterprises in Taiwan.
The DEI only policies are relatively implemented in big business and SMEs in Taiwan.
We still see a majority of them.
We still need to see government show their support for DEI implementation.
Any other people?
Please.
These women's rights and sustainable development association.
So this morning, our review committee mentioned about this balance of raising children and work.
So I think the Ministry of Labor gave a response that mainly focused on fragmented measures they have and the solutions they have.
However, we are not seeing overarching system change and overarching strategies.
For example, that nurses in Taiwan, we see a very high attrition rate.
And these nurses, they have to take like night shifts and they have to take care of the patients and as well as their families.
But it's really difficult to retain the nurses.
The nurses should not individually shoulder up the so-called family and career balance is about a time management issue.
Or should we actually take a systematic national institution as protection for them so they can better serve their patients?
And for health care,
Any other NGO representatives?
Please turn off your microphone in the NGO seats.
Thank you very much for all the additional imputes and perspectives from the civil society.
I think they're very well noted.
I don't see any questions for CSO.
So we will now turn to Article 12 and open the floor also for first time speakers in the first instance.
Thank you.
We are focusing on Article 12.
So we are going to give the floor first to those who hasn't made comments in the first row.
So this is the Taiwan Mental Health Association.
We would like to urge the review committee to factor in that mental health as a critical element of women's health because we always focus on women's physical health.
We actually neglected the mental health aspects.
And then for our association, we are doing a lot of work in the community.
And in our practice, we observe that a lot of the mental difficulties come from stigmatization about gender based violence and exclusion of education.
So it's all tied together.
And in Taiwan, we actually take a very piecemeal solution.
And also they are overly medicalized.
Therefore, we would like to ask the government to establish a mental health policy to further build and enhance and empower the victims, their resilience.
And also we would like to see a support system and training for mental health people with mental disabilities.
And also we see the women with neurodivergence can also enjoy a safe environment without stigmatization.
So this is the Taiwan Mother's Shield Association.
When government promotes the egg freezing policies without disclosing fully the risks, for example, the risk of cancer inducing procedures.
And also they did not actually disclose the risks of stillbirth.
And then also in Taiwan that we actually see the lesbian couples using the in vitro procedures.
It's pretty much like a surrogate.
It's in practice a surrogacy approach.
And then also for the surrogacy, it's putting a lot of risks on the surrogacy mothers.
And we don't really have a lot of regulation, a risk evaluation for this parental relationship recognition legally.
And then I think the assisted reproductive procedure should go back to the purpose of the medical purse.
And our draft has been excluding the application of civil code of article number 1067.
So the sperm donor cannot, the offspring of the sperm donor would not really know who the birth father is for the entirety of their life.
It's a violation of children's rights.
And Taiwan's LGBT family rights of advocacy to answer the question that the assisted reproductive technology is only limited to heterosexual couples, even though there is a draft amendment.
However, there is no guarantee that this draft bill will be adopted in the legislative.
We would like to urge the government to take active approach.
And then also we don't see any researchers or statistic numbers to actually see the impact, a potential impact for those people of need.
And if we cannot accelerate this amendment, then we would like to urge the government to conduct researches to accelerate the reformation.
And also there should be supportive measures in place.
For example, anti-discriminatory measures to make sure that those users of these assistive technologies would not be discriminated against.
Second role.
This is the Taiwan Birthright Reform Association about obstetrics violence.
So in your question, you actually mentioned that the government should actually provide information of the numbers of the obstetrics violence numbers.
It was not answered this morning.
I think this is actually because our government failed to understand the different types and the profiles of obstetrics violence,
because international society has already seek the obstetrics violence reduction.
So I think in Taiwan, not only marginalized women suffer from obstetrics violence,
the majority of the women, they actually suffer different degrees of obstetrics violence without consent procedures being taken and no privacy protected.
And then also there was no risk disclosed.
So it's a violation of CEDAW.
Therefore, I think the measure should, they should start to adopt measure to collect the data.
So this is the Judicial Reform Foundation.
So according to the response by the Ministry of Welfare,
we are very positive that they're already removing the draft, in the draft that dispossesses consent for abortion.
However, we saw that they said they're continuing to collecting the opinions of religious groups.
So I would like to know the timetable for the amendment of the draft.
And then also, do they have the plan to submit for Legislative Yuan?
The women's reproductive rights is protected by, and autonomy is protected by constitution.
I think we should avoid that amendment of the law being delayed due to differences in opinion.
And therefore, we would like to ask the review committee to urge the government to ask the Ministry of Health to give a specific timetable.
So the first time the National Bar Association, so Article 12, that the women still need a spousal consent for abortion.
I would like to talk about that.
The first CEDAW recommendation has already asked there should be a removal of spousal consent for abortion.
However, ever since the last review, there was no specific progress made.
Even the Ministry of Welfare and Health responded that they are still working on it, but they are still collecting opinions.
So that was their response.
However, it's not actually changing anything that marriage women without spousal consent,
when they go through an abortion procedure, they will still be charged with criminal code violation.
Therefore, we would like to urge the committee to urge the government to take a more active approach rather than collecting opinions only.
And also, we would like to urge the government to show a timetable rather than further kicking the can down the road.
Article 12, Taiwan Association of Gender Sexuality Rights Protection for the Surrogacy and Assisted Reproductive Rights.
It should not only talk about reproductive autonomy of women, it will affect women's and children's health.
So I think there should be a full disclosure of the risks involved and also the health risks to teen minors and children and the women.
And then because for these assisted reproductive procedures, they need to inject a great amount of hormones,
and it's going to induce a high percentage of cancer and then pregnancy,
chronicle diseases and high blood pressure and then also for children and the health risks is a lot higher.
It's actually 1.5 to 6 times higher health risks.
And there may be occurrence of critical diseases like children's cancer, high blood pressure,
and also the genotype presentation of the gene may change.
And there are neurodevelopment issues.
Therefore, these assisted reproductive procedures not only affect women's health, but also children's health.
Thank you.
Taiwan Parents Protect Women and Children Association.
My apologies, I wasn't aware of the routine, so I mentioned Article 12 at Article 10.
I would like to say that the sexual diseases in Taiwan, including AIDS and syphilis,
in 2021 to 2026, from the ages 15 to 26, there is an increase, especially the female patients is higher than male,
and female syphilis is higher than female.
These female sexual diseases see a higher increase by 10 to 21 percent,
and I think the significance of these numbers should be reviewed.
We should see a statistics review of this, but we don't see the government doing this job right now,
and we think the government should do so.
Thank you.
This is the Garden of Hope Foundation.
The reproductive rights of female is about law protection,
and it's whether female can really exercise their autonomy and rights.
In recent years, Taiwan has been promoting gender equality,
but the women are still unable to cease pregnancy or emergency pregnancy prevention,
and especially minor women from remote areas, they see an intersectionality of the risks.
They need to pay a higher cost to access the same medical services.
So we urge the government to follow Article 12 of CEDAW,
and to give women back their rights and autonomy to reproduction,
and also remove the requirement for spousal consent for abortion.
Thank you.
We are the Lianglin Education Association,
and we would like to look at the mental health facilitation and counseling of pregnant women.
We think this is about post-remedy, and it lacks the front-end social support.
A lot of the pregnant women are facing postpartum depression,
and they are unable to leave their house,
or they are too busy taking care of children and unable to leave their house.
So I think the government should work with CSOs to build family resilience programs,
combining the spouses and family support network.
We are now lacking the prevention.
This is an unspoken discrimination against women.
We should develop preventive family resilience and interactive programs.
This is the Women's Rescue Foundation.
We believe assisted reproduction technology should be discussed differently from surrogacy.
For over the two decades, surrogacy has been wrapped in package in discussion with assisted reproduction,
but assisted reproduction act is about different people,
and surrogacy is about people who commission the surrogacy.
If we combine the two, then this is just making it too easy,
but making it very easy for the discussion, but difficult for the legislation.
Therefore, we think that the assisted reproduction act amendment
should first deal with allowing single women and female spouses to use the technology,
so that people who really need this do not miss their opportunity for reproduction.
An advancement of children rights.
Recently, I read a secondary school sexually education guide, and I feel concerned.
For example, the guide includes a first-person description of sexual violence
and uses drinking tea as a metaphor for sexual intercourse.
As a student, I worry that these activities could cause distrust to students who have experienced trauma
and may also lead to embarrassment, teasing, or secondary harm during classroom discussions.
CEDAW article 10 and 12 call for a safer environment and the protection of women's physical and mental health.
I respectfully encourage the government to reveal its teaching materials
to ensure that sexuality education protects girls instead of creating additional psychological pressure.
Thank you.
Next, the fifth row on the right-hand side.
This is the Taiwan Disabled Women's Alliance for Equal Rights.
We've talked about women's rights for disabilities.
Earlier on, the government responded that there are over 2,000 clinics,
but only 7.5 percent of the clinics are subsidized by people with disabilities or women with disabilities
if they need to go to the clinics and they have children that need to accompany them.
It's very difficult for them to use these facilities, and women with disabilities,
when they go to hospitals, even though there are accessible facilities, it's difficult for them to use,
especially for when we go through different examinations.
We recommend that the demo sites should continue to be promoted, and second, with these reward programs,
they should be adjusted because even though the clinics are selected for these reward programs,
they would say you cannot receive checkup here.
This is the Alliance for Independent Living in Taiwan.
Even though the Ministry of Health and Welfare talked about accessibility facilities,
but women with disabilities, we still rely on the goodwill of the clinics,
and it depends on whether the clinic actually has real accessible facilities for us to enter.
So I think there should be a systematic review of all of these facilities
so that we have the accessible facilities.
Right now, there are also urban and remote area gaps for these rural area gaps for women with disabilities.
The higher the disability, they need to pay more out of their own pockets to hire people to help them.
So we think there should be personal assistance provided to women with disabilities,
and also there should be reasonable accommodation made to these clinics and medical environments to provide us assistance,
but so far there are no comprehensive and effective plans.
The medical information in Taiwan lacking, for example, reasonable accommodation.
It's very difficult to ensure that women with disabilities can access the medical services required.
In addition, there are hospitals with accessible facilities,
but in addition to facilities, we need accessible provision of medical knowledge.
And right now, we need support for women with disabilities.
And there are still medical personnel who are more protective,
and this mentality of protectionism will affect the health of women with disabilities and their autonomy to pregnancy.
And I hope that medical institutions should have relevant trainings for all of these accessibilities.
This is the Covenant's Watch.
I would like to respond to the Foreign Domestic Workers' Rights.
It involves their work rights and their health rights.
The government has a lot of outreach and campaigns for them,
but because they are not covered under our Labor's Basic Act,
so they rely on the goodwill of the employees,
and governments don't really understand about the conditions of their life and work.
For example, what's the percentage of the privacy violation,
or what's the percentage of sexual harassment or sexual assault?
Are they able to take rest when they are feeling unwell,
or do they have access to medical services?
So please recommend the government to follow ILO 189 to draft relevant legislative protections.
Thank you.
This is the Taiwan Association for Gender, the Taiwan Equality Campaign.
In 2024, we have various surveys, and the support for assisted reproduction is 70%,
and that's the latest survey we have for two women to get married
and to be able to produce their own children through assisted reproduction.
We currently have a draft.
We should encourage the adoption of the Act,
and we hope that women in Taiwan, whether or not they are married or not,
they can use assisted reproduction to bear their own child despite their sexual orientation.
This is the Awakening Foundation.
We would like to talk about the post-event prevention towards the contraceptive pills,
the morning after contraceptive pills.
Right now, Taiwan requires that you need a prescription to buy contraceptive pills,
but the reality is even if you don't have a prescription, you can get it,
and the government is enforcing that remote areas cannot,
we are worried that there are women who cannot access contraceptive pills during holidays and weekends,
and with the OB-GYN decreasing their accessions,
they are unable to gain access to these contraceptive pills,
and we hope we don't violate their privacy along the way as well.
Taiwan Parents Shield Association, third time making comments.
I would like to raise the issue about making the emergency contraceptive pill available over the counter.
There are different approaches in different countries.
In Taiwan, it's still a prescriptive pill that is required to have doctor's prescription,
but I think it makes sense because we cannot only explain this about women's body and health autonomy.
So, for example, there are the hormones percentages actually one to eight times of the general contraceptive pill.
Some of the doctors are recommending that this kind of contraceptive pill for emergency use
should be prevented from taking more than three times a year,
and then 60 percent of the parents think that for those teenage girls under age 18
should not have access to emergency contraceptive pills.
Taiwan Hotline Association, for the LGBT groups' access to health care,
that according to the Ministry of Health in 2024, they have a guideline for LGBT health care,
but for these transgender people, their experience in practice,
according to our survey made by the Hotline Association,
30 percent of the transgender people would actually avoid going to doctors because of this intolerance in the medical setting,
and then we would need to change the first-line medical health care's attitude.
It's critical, but still not enough, because we also need to improve the entire medical setting hardware and systems.
And also, for transgender people, they don't have enough of medical resources available for them.
For example, according to the survey, a lot of these transgender people think that where they are,
they don't have access to enough of medical resources,
and then also there is a disparity between West and Eastern part of Taiwan,
and there is a disparity of urban and rural areas. Thank you.
I would like to also talk about transgender people's access to health care.
According to the Ministry of Health, we have 99 percent of national health insurance coverage in Taiwan,
but I would like to remind our review committee that, for example, the transgender people,
they need hormones, treatment, and then that treatment is excluded, not reimbursed by national health insurance.
So we can see the unfriendliness of these health care workers toward transgender people,
and then also they have to pay a high percentage out of their own pocket for their own health care,
and also a lot of teens, they had to actually go underground to buy the hormone pills,
so they are facing huge health risks.
Therefore, we would like to urge that the national health insurance should also include reimbursement
for the medical needs for transgender people, and also the health care workers,
they should improve their awareness of transgender people's situation.
We should see a balance of disparity between urban and rural areas,
and also the Executive Yuan draft is excluding transgender people entirely.
Taiwan Mother Shield Alliance, again, second time, about those emergency contraceptive pills,
the pharmacists, for over-the-counter non-prescription requirement,
the pharmacists, they need additional training, and if we make this over-the-counter available,
then ER is going to further exacerbate the sexual exploitation,
and if they can go to get a contraceptive pill by going to the doctors,
and then there is a touch point for these required reporting of the possible sexual exploitation of teens and children,
because the doctors in the clinic would ask about the last time period,
when did that come, and whether they are pregnant,
so I think the teenage girls need more than just one pill, they need to be seen, they need to be protected,
and also in Japan, the pharmacists need to provide this one-to-one consultation,
and they need further training, and also a parent's companion is also required.
NGO, sitting in the back row.
This Women Rescue Foundation, when it comes to digital gender-based violence,
a lot of women are suffering from cyber gender-based violence,
and then that leads to photo stigmatization, and there is self-stigmatization that leads to mental health issues,
and then that is borrowing them from going to schools and then find employment.
Even the government actually are subsidizing up to three times of counseling services,
but the quota is exhausted very early on in many of the counties and cities.
I think for the sexual intimacy images of violence, we need to see more support from the government,
therefore we would like to urge the government to give more support to those victims of cyber gender-based violence.
The Twin Association of Taiwan, we would like to emphasize again,
be it to assistive reproductive act or the protection for these older pregnant women
that the government said there are only 158 cases of that,
but actually for these twins cases, they are all the old age pregnant women,
and also we are not seeing any statistics and data,
and then there is no figures, and then I think these twins issues are the hidden figure.
This is the issue that we need to raise, and we would like to see the government need to recognize the severity of the issue,
and also be it this pregnancy and prenatal care, and also the assisted reproductive care needed by the women
that we are not seeing any of the mental health support for these kind of women.
Workshops are not enough.
You need to actually hold their hands to actually show them the differences in culture
and to actually give them different support accordingly.
Thank you very much.
Anyone who hasn't talked yet?
Taiwan LGBT Family Advocacy Group, so that the government are actually providing family health support
to heterosexual families for LGBTQ families' needs.
They don't have enough understanding.
For example, a public funded these vaccines.
For example, the newborn baby within six months of their birth, they cannot take the vaccine.
However, for their physical care, the parents should be able to have access to the vaccines.
However, like we mentioned yesterday, the same sex lesbian couples,
they need to adopt the children because they are the legal strangers.
Therefore, they don't have access to that free vaccine.
So that is a big gap of health care, and also a lot of policies would still identify its mothers and fathers,
so that is excluding different types of families.
To representative in the back row, Taiwan Mother's Shield Alliance.
I would like to offer additional information.
Executive Yuan, when they submitted the draft for Assisted Reproductive Act,
so we did a national wide survey, 80% of the people are against making the assistive reproductive technology
to lesbian couples in a single woman, so they are against that.
That is a number for the review committee and for the emergency contraceptive pill.
I think we should really take factor into the needs of the teenage girls
because the majority of the needs come from the teenage girls,
so I think we need to be very careful and cautious in that regard.
Article 12, any other additional comments and input?
Taiwan Association of Gender Sexuality writes about this sexuality health.
I think the sexuality teachers' number on campuses are far from enough,
and then the implementation of sexuality health education is far from enough.
Therefore, I urge the government and the state to adopt concrete research
numbers and also the need to employ professionally trained educators
for these campus, on-campus training.
And second time making the comments on the Taiwan Association for Sexuality Education
when it comes to emergency contraceptive pill.
Teenage girls, when it comes to avoiding pregnancy,
that if you make this available, they are going to pop the pills on the regular basis.
Therefore, they would not be fusing, for example, unprotected sex,
or they would not want to use, for example, condoms for these kind of regular contraceptive measures.
So they are just popping the pills.
Then it's going to lead to these huge risks to their health.
This is something we need to take into consideration.
And also, as an educator, I have to urge that professional organizations
are critical to delivering professional sexuality education.
I would like to urge the state to take a neutral stance,
because we have been doing this for a very long time to help the state.
Do not brand us as an outcast.
This should not be happening.
Article 12, anyone want to make comments?
The Twin Association.
So on behalf of Mental Health Association in Taiwan, mental health is very important.
But in all the discussion, we have assistive reproduction, be it health education.
But you're not talking about mental health at all, and even the National Health Agency.
When you talk about mental health, they would ask you to go to the mental health office.
So I think you should not have these bipolar approach.
It should not be a binary approach.
It's not like you have the mental health on the one side.
You have these different physical issues on the one hand.
You should take these two tiers approach at the same time.
Mental health is very important.
We need to pay more attention to that.
And then also, like we said, disadvantaged groups.
For example, these people suffering from mental and physical disabilities,
they also need mental health rather than rushing in the help after the crisis, after the fact.
And we don't have enough funding for that.
Thank you.
And then before we return the time back to the Madame Chair, any other comments to make?
Madame Chair.
Thank you very much.
I appreciate all of the comments and the perspectives that were shared on articles 10, 11, and 12.
But I would, however, want to, since we have a little time on our hands,
get some CSO perspectives on the issue of unpaid care,
because nobody spoke about it in your interventions.
What is the view of the civil society about calculating?
Because a lot of the questions and the comments you're raising actually are linked with inadequate data
and information on the size of your unpaid care economy
and the amount of work that is done either in the former or the informal sector,
which now affects employability and income of women and men differently.
So do you have any views or comments of that?
That's one.
And then we also put to the government the issue of national standards on work valuation.
Any views, any comments from the civil society before we rise for lunch break?
Any comments? No views?
So based on these unpaid labor, do we have any other comments coming from the CSOs?
So I have to say, when it comes to these long-term care calculation and surveys,
we don't have sufficient work in that, because in Taiwan, ever since 2025,
we didn't have these kind of surveys accumulated over the years.
The only one we have is the Ministry of Health on a regular basis.
They actually have the survey of the women's living condition, but it's not comprehensive.
They're only targeting women from age 15 to 60 years old.
And when it comes to this comparison of unpaid labor,
they actually survey and sample women aged between 15 to 60.
And if they have these co-living spouse,
and then they would actually survey the women with co-living spouse.
But that is the only source of information we have, but it's actually highly inaccurate,
because it's overlooking, for example, these young caretakers on paid labor.
And also, we see these taking care of the old,
and those are not really factored into the national survey.
Any other additional comment to make?
I personally worked as the local government or central government gender equality commission commissioner.
And from my experiences, female unpaid labor is on a larger level than male.
And in addition to time, the females spend more time,
actually three times higher than the time that the male partner spends on housework and child care.
Even though the survey is not perfect, it's an indication.
In a lot of the volunteer trainings in different governments,
we noticed that female volunteers has a higher number than male.
Myself, as a gender equality commissioner, I encourage more male to work as volunteers.
We encourage housework balance, of course.
But that requires other systems for facilitation.
Any other responses?
This is the world the Taiwan Mothers Show Alliance.
According to survey, the real policy we want is economic equality and equal subsidies.
There are a lot of mothers taking care of their own child.
Mothers that take care of their own child are not higher than daycare services.
And for these household daycare personnel, they don't have parental leave, and they are criticized by the parents.
We hope that society continues to encourage us.
If we can receive subsidy, even if we raise our own child,
I'm sure there are more parents who are willing to give birth to a second child.
This is the Taipei Independent Living in Taiwan.
And if there are children with disabilities, female usually become the main caretaker.
And it comes a lot from the lack of public service for people with disabilities.
For example, when we go to schools, even though there are budgets for assistance,
but it's very difficult to access such budget or to initiate these access,
because there are different severities of disabilities.
And schools, they often ask mothers to come to school with them to support their entire schooling process.
And this unpaid and overworked assistance is unfair to women.
A mother needs to do the work of two to three people.
In addition to the housework, they need to assist 24 hours for their children with disabilities.
So we encourage the government to provide comprehensive assistance to the domestic requirements.
Actually, I would like to point out and remind ourselves that in Sustainable Development Goals, SDG,
number five on gender equality and empowerment of women and girls,
the target 5.4 is about this unpaid domestic work,
which I read, recognize and value unpaid care and domestic work through the provision of public services.
That's exactly what you are talking about, whether for women with disabilities or ordinary women.
Through the provision of public services, infrastructure and social protection policies,
and the promotion of shared responsibility within the household and the family as nationally appropriate.
So it should be provided by the public service, but also by the shared responsibility within each household.
And then I heard that you had this survey on women's living conditions, which is not comprehensive.
And that shows how the work is divided within the family, between men and women, between the spouses.
But also it should be provided in the public, through the public services.
But usually that area is underpaid.
And then it is primarily women who work for the facilities, for the disabled people,
for the children or elderly people who are severely underpaid.
And that's what brings the gender pay gap,
because women work primarily in the areas where the pay is low while men are paid.
So it is a very important issue how the society and the family divide the work that's necessary for our everyday survival.
And then you need the social discussion on this issue.
And in addition to that, I see there is clear differences among different NGOs regarding many issues on sexuality education,
on campuses in education, as well as this assisted reproductive act, et cetera.
And then also whether morning after a pill should be available over the counter or by prescription.
And I think it happens in other countries, too.
And I think these conflicting opinions, CEDAW Convention does not dictate what specific guidance or rules or regulations each country should have.
So you need to come up with a social consensus.
But in that, the government should do active role, not just wait, OK, collecting information, as someone has already pointed out,
but government should come up with proactive role in promoting equality,
balancing and trying to form a consent, social consensus on this some very controversial issues.
So that's my we will not come up with a very concrete, exact, you should take this role or this policy or this amendment
unless it comes to the really fundamental thing.
Our review committee cannot provide you with whether you should have certain word in school curriculum, in sexuality education.
It's beyond our role as international review committee.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Dr. Haso.
I think just weighing on that, some comments were talking about the content of educational material.
And it's important for you to know that CEDAW recommendation actually, the GR actually states age appropriate sexual education.
So sexual educational materials for adolescents cannot be the same as for children and
cannot be the same as for undergraduates or the same as for post-graduate students.
So CEDAW doesn't prescribe.
It's not a prescriptive recommendation.
It suggests and gives guidance to states and to society to find the appropriate.
I don't think it's consensus to find the midway.
But in all of that, it has to be appropriate, age appropriate, because what I heard some CSOs speak about in my country
will stir a huge debate because such language would never be accepted in educational material for I mean,
unless it was at the university level.
And even then, the way it is structured is very important.
And so you as a society have an obligation and you are associations,
you are clusters of individuals who have a voice and who are trying to protect the interests of groups.
And so you have the responsibility to monitor, to guide and to work with government.
Perhaps there were errors in materials that were circulated.
They can always be recalled and they can always be reviewed.
That's why policies are constantly reviewed.
That's why the law is constantly reformed, because it might have been good maybe three years ago because society was ready for it.
Then if there are changes in society, you also have to change, you know,
or if you send out those materials and you see they're not appropriate and they are heading the society in a direction that is not agreeable,
then you have the obligation to guide government, work with government to say, you know,
we maybe thought this was OK three years ago or five years ago, but this has been the impact.
And you hear us repeatedly asking about the impacts because when you make these changes, they will lead to some social change.
Are they positive or are they negative?
Your job is to monitor and to advise and to work with government to say these materials should not be for this certain age grade,
perhaps for certain settings where there's maturity, they're adults, you know, and they can handle it.
But it all depends on your social context.
Nothing is ever in isolation.
And so you need to keep that at the back of your mind, you know, when you make your recommendations.
And we also will be guided by that.
CEDAW has its own framework.
And in that framework, particularly for sexual education, it is age appropriate.
And the reason it says age appropriate is so that it reduces exploitation based on ignorance at a younger age.
If a child doesn't know the appropriate name, the language, then they can be exploited and they can be lured and they can be deceived.
But if you package the information that is appropriate for their age, at least they then know when to seek help.
And they can within the family setting, you know, know when the people are crossing the boundaries
or they are speaking to them in inappropriate ways or touching or handling them in ways that are inappropriate.
All those are supposed to be safeguards.
They are not intended to erode the values of any society.
If you recall the opening remarks yesterday is that CEDAW is not adversarial.
It's actually to enrich a society, increase the safeguards, increase protection so that overall the society has better cohesion, more protective and more productive.
And I hope that, yes, should be a constant what we have at the back of our minds at all times as we're making these recommendations.
Professor Heysen.
I think it's in addition to age appropriate, I think it should be scientifically evidenced.
And with full protection of privacy.
So and then every society is different, you know, from that.
It should not be morally judged or otherwise.
I think we've earned ourselves a little more time.
I think 15 more minutes and we can add that to our lunch time.
We want to thank you for all of the contributions for shedding light on areas that we didn't know.
And we wish you a good lunch break.
And we look forward to our convening back here after lunch, I believe at two o'clock.
Thank you very much and have a lovely day.
Thank you very much to our international review committee members and all of you for your participation.
We now would like to have a lunch break.
We'll be back by two o'clock in the afternoon.
We have lunch boxes ready outside.
Please help yourselves.
Thank you. We'll see you in the afternoon. Thank you.
welcome back everyone and to start the abdomen session we will continue on
with the review of core document articles 13 to 14 now why you go to be
and now to begin back to our Madonna chair
thank you very much and welcome back everyone I hope we had a good lunch and
time to stretch our legs and have a health break we will now go on to article
13 we're happy to have the minister back with us the head of delegation and we
will promptly yield the floor to Professor Nickers to take us through
you have to thank you madam chair we are now turning to article 13 in the seat of
convention and I recall that when when article 10 is dealing with education
article 11 with employment article 12 with health then in article 13 it stated
that state parties shall take all appropriate measures to eliminate
discrimination against women in other areas of economic and social life in
order to ensure on a basis of equality of men and women the same rights so this
is a kind of of article which is is then covering in a sense the rest of
different areas which are not covered by these earlier articles I will address
or raise three issues under article 13 first we have noted many concerns not at
least from the side of the NGOs regarding gender-friendly restrooms and
all gender restrooms we have learned from the government that on all gender
restroom friendliness inspection guidance and improvement plan has been
adopted in April 26 very recently by the government please explain what really
have been the concerns here and how this concern have been addressed by this new
plan in April 26 my second question relates once again to female migrant
workers we learned that they are not eligible to participate in the national
pension insurance system since the migrant workers predominantly are female
and they amount to a huge number 280,000 has been mentioned one can ask whether
we do not have a case of indirect discrimination here we understand that
this lack of protection is a consequence of their employment status but from the
point of view of article 13 I think we have a real problem here my third issue
question relates to trade agreements and the economic empowerment and gender
equality considerations how they are included in the context of trade
agreements which Taiwan is part of here the government refers to some measures
that have been taking and that they are taking care of the inclusion of gender
equality consideration here they refer to women's participation in exhibitions
and training my question is have there been any inclusion in this context of the
UN business and human rights approach where for instance the position of vulnerable
groups in supply chains could be addressed thank you very much these were my three
questions thank you madam chair and I thank my colleague professor Nicholas for
introducing this article 13 and there are two other aspects that I'd like to
address here and one of them concerns the issue of the taxation regime in in
Taiwan and I note that in your responses to the list of issues you say that you
impact assessments in regard to formulating or amending tax laws and I note that there
is a mixture of progressive and regressive taxation in Taiwan and one of the
regressive taxations has to do with the value-added tax that is levied on on
and as you're aware it's a it's a consumption tax and a regressive tax and low
income households spend a larger proportion of their income on necessities
compared to higher income households and so most there are women who are adversely
impacted by that in regard to their spending a higher percentage of their overall
earnings on that and so if you say that you do gender impact assessments how did
you assess this that tax in regard to women and their its impact on their on
their socioeconomic empowerment and development so that's one question the
other one concerns the issue that I'm Professor Nicholas has just brought up
and that's the the trade agreements that Taiwan would engage in again in your
list of issue responses you say that you do pre and post negotiation gender
impact assessments and so my question would be how did you evaluate and assess
one or two or all of your trade agreements in regard to how they affect
women's human rights as you know and as has been said the supply chains often
adversely affect women women workers and and marginalized women and so I'd like
to hear your views on how your gender impact assessments in terms of trade
agreements have been evaluated and what the results are because it seems to me
that there are structural challenges implicit in in trade agreements and
policy initiatives which need to be really considered in regard to women and
women's empowerment and inclusion and lastly we've talked a lot about the care
economy and I just want to look at that briefly again under article 13 and ask
recognition of the care economy and the fact that globally women perform the
vast majority of unpaid care work and also paid care work is severely
undervalued in in in most societies and I'd like to know how Taiwan evaluates
the care economy and the fact that women step in the gap where when when
countries or states parties do not provide the kinds of services women take
care of the elderly they take care of children they take care of the sick and
perform a lot of unpaid care that goes unrecognized in the general domestic
product the GDP and so my questions are around the recognition of the care
economy and and how Taiwan approaches this not only recognizing it but perhaps
making it part of the GDP compensating women for the unpaid care that they
carried out where they fill in the gaps of public services that the that the
state party does not do and and so I'd like your response to this issue of the
economy and how you address the impacts that it has on women's rights thank you
thank you very much I think I would probably want to add one or two
questions want to seek further insights on the trade relations and the
I know like in my country there's a very robust trade agreement with some credit
guarantees for export but you find that women entrepreneurs and women traders
and exporters and SMEs really do not have equitable access to those credit
guarantees as their male counterparts so the question is besides your gender
impact assessment is there any mechanism that you have in place to
ensure that this trade credit guarantees gender responsive and that there are
certain benchmarks within it to ensure that both men and women producers and
exporters get access to that credit scheme the second is when we spoke about
national machineries and we talked about financing gender financing you
elaborated on how gender responsive budgeting is being used in the public
sector to try to drive gender equality the question is in the private sector
and across different value chains and companies of different values
particularly the high-end companies do you have any gender procurement
mechanism in place or a policy as a country because that's a policy that has
gained a lot of global traction with the global procurement global campaign
launched by the International Trade Center and UN Women last year at the
DSW is Taiwan aware of that do you have any mechanism to utilize gender
responsive procurement to breach inequalities in the private sector
between the high-end companies and the smaller companies I would be curious to
know that thank you very much
yeah thank you very much for your questions you each have two three
questions one overarching question is regarding trade agreement three
reviewers mentioned this and regarding trade agreement we will have the economic
trade office Ministry of Economic Affairs and FSC to answer these
questions and the FSC is broadening because you talked about credit
guarantee so we're we'll have we will bring in these three agencies for the
questions first of all following the order of the questions we will have the
environment department to talk about gender inclusive facilities especially
the toilets and secondly regarding the female migrant worker labor insurance
system that will be taken by the Ministry of Labor and thirdly the after
the Ministry of Labor explains the labor insurance system the they will all we
will ask the trade agreement related agencies to answer the questions and
we'll have the Ministry of Finance to talk about the tax systems especially
low-income families and the consumer tax for this daily necessities and the
impact to household caring females and for a care economy we will ask Ministry
of Labor and House Health and Welfare to answer the question and the final
question in addition to the trade agreements that we will answer together
your second question was about financing we will have FSC take this question and
there is a question about the gender budgeting this is the budget for gender
procurement
so the tax impact gender impact evaluation so these questions will be
answered by these respective agencies first of all we start with the Ministry
of Department environmental protection this is the office of environmental
management you mentioned the gender inclusive facility data shows that the
qualities are inconsistent and there are unreasonable situations in April 22nd
this year we drafted a program to improve the survey of gender friendly
toilets and it's working with the local governments to inspect all of the gender
friendly toilets around Taiwan and to guide its improvements we hope to work
with the National Planning Agency which in 2024 2025 round about a year or two
we came up with we drafted a guideline for gender friendly toilets hoping that all
gender friendly toilets can fulfill and achieve the standards including security
and privacy if anyone talk about years please use the Western dates the Western
years thank you next we would like to invite the Ministry of Labor to explain
and answer the labor insurance system for female migrant workers according to
our current labor insurance credit act any employer that hires over five people
they need to have its mandatory that all employees must be covered by labor
insurance and employees under four people will be voluntary if they are
covered by the labor insurance in the future they can apply for our pension or
disability pension and so on and according to the act for OSH all employees
that are the labor occupational accident insurance anyone covered in this
they need to take lessons and trainings in OSH going into the trade agreements
which is a question raised by all three reviewers we will ask our three agencies
to answer the question this is the first one at the economic and trade office
regarding the question you asked about female empowerment and gender equality
in terms of legal and legislation and policies in starting from 2009 we have
promoted the gender impact evaluation in significant policy and bills and in
2022 the gender equality Commission at executive UN passed an agreement on
bilateral agreement on international conventions to conduct gender impact
evaluation and it we also established a national level gender decision-making
monitoring mechanism in terms of international and public participation
group employment economy and welfare groups we all have gender equality
experts from CSOs participating in the Commission and we will regularly
investigate whether or not the government has promoted gender
mainstreaming and gender impact evaluation in the bills and policies and
through gender impact evaluation combined with gender statistics and
analysis we monitor how trade agreements impact women economic
empowerment and gender equality and to make sure that the perspectives are
included to improve gender inequality and then using the gender statistics
and indicators in Ministry of Economic Affairs we all of our activities
will collect these data for evaluation for example the women participation
in international trade and as working as entrepreneurs and employment and in
support of female entrepreneur and entrepreneurship and SME entrepreneurship
and to lower the impact of female SME by trade agreements we work with them to
receive training and also funding to improve their international trade
participation for example participating in the trade agreement with our trade
partner and you UK which is ETP and to improve the women empower economic
empowerment and at the of administrate the agency of SME we also have a female
startup program and also the 21st century trade agreement for Taipei and
during drought while we're drafting the bills and policies we take into
consideration of the stakeholders including female the minorities and
including high-standard and inclusive clauses to protect and facilitate the
protection of female and indigenous peoples to make sure that women are not
discriminated against in international trade and next would be Ministry of
Economic Affairs this is the International Trade Office at MOEA and
female participation and how economic trade agreement impacts following up
with the previous answer in terms of our implementation of the trade
agreements will make sure that there are no measures that put female rights in
adversity and we work hard to facilitate female participation in international
trade activities and help them participate in domestic and international
exhibitions and and take they take training courses training courses to
empower them economically and at the FSC we continue to encourage financial
institutions to help female obtain funding starting from 2013 we take the
indicators we take into indicators the result of female SME entrepreneurs
financing results and we encourage if our financial institutions to work with
female onto SME entrepreneurships and they should have the equal opportunities
in obtaining funding and regarding the volume of financing for female
entrepreneurship in SME there was a 2.4 trillion by new Taiwanese dollars by
20 end of 2025 and it grew up from it it was an increase of 6.39 percent next we
would like to invite Ministry of Finance to explain the taxation system versus
gender impact evaluation regarding the questions mentioned in how we we have
amended our tax systems and when we do this we conduct gender impact assessment
basically the checklists include gender statistics and gender analysis and during
the evaluation we note to see if there are any gender inequalities and we invite
external reviewers and experts and scholars to make sure that the taxation
system does not cause inequality in gender and as mentioned by our reviewers
our business tax does not target low-income or mid low-income female in
providing lower taxes or waves waving of the taxes when they're purchasing this
daily necessities but it's mainly to have to avoid preferential treatment in
taxes so we do not have different tax treatments for different genders but to
implement gender equality and lower the burden economic burden of female
procurement we make sure that there are other lower costs in implementation to
make sure that the mid and low-income female in procuring daily necessities
they can benefit from a lower cost and in turn lowering their financial burden
thank you then we go into care economy we would like to invite the Ministry of
Labor to take this question followed by Minister of Health and Welfare okay
this is the Labor Development Office regarding the unpaid care work and
domestic work starting from 2026 January 1st we have a flexible parental leave
basically by facilitating flexible parental leaves it encourages the male
to also participate in child rearing and at the Ministry of Health and Welfare
social insurance directorate we have pensions for occupational
insurances and for these non-officially earning female in order to implement
universal care for everyone starting from 2020 2008 we have a national pension
system anyone over the age of 25 and under the age of 65 if you don't have
labor military or civil servant insurances you are included in this
universal national pension and when there are insurance incidents they can
claim payments and we also adjust according to the changes this time we
23.5 and we also if the CPI now the CPI growth rate has reached 30% we will
consider to paying for the other necessities and also for the non-earning
women they can also be protected in this way so on the care economy the
Department of Gender Equality would like to chip in as well this is
Executive Yuan Department of Gender Equality additional information to
offer here and on your when it comes to a care economy how do we reflect care
economy in our GPT so far we don't have statistics factoring our care economy
in our GDP however according to international labor organization and
also the UN survey we do recognize that around the globe we see a lot amount of
unpaid work mostly domestic work of taking care of elders if you want to
convert that into economy numbers is going to account for 10 to 39 percent of
the GD global GDP therefore this is actually an international trend which
has already recognized the value and social contribution of unpaid care
economy and then it's just as important as utility infrastructure and
transportation work therefore we are going to provide we are committed to
provide this public available care network which can lessen the burden on
the caregivers and because of that Executive Yuan are also working together
with other ministries to give complimentary services to further
bolster up the social network for long-term care and also inclusive
workplace and paternity leave and also parental leave so we also recognize the
women are suffering from this pay gap due to the disruption of their
career so they can further to pursue their own self-realization also we also
want to avoid this older women poverty due to this care economy and also we
want to turn the tide on the stereotype impression of men working and then the
woman taking care of the family that is very important to recognize the value of
unpaid work so that people of different genders can still contribute to the
society and also shoulder up and share the burden of family care and also we
are enhancing the residual division of property in terms of the revision of a
civil coach and we are now working on the pension reformation as well thank
you coming back to the questions raised before we actually talk about the
credit assurance and then I would like to ask the Ministry of Labor and also
CIP Council of Indigenous Peoples would you like to also offer information on
credit guarantees maybe the Ministry of Labor go first and then Ministry of
Economy so from the Ministry of Labor in order to lessen the burden of women
entrepreneurs we have these microloan for them so the maximum number of the
loan provided is two million they don't need to offer the warranties and
guarantees and then also they can be free of interest for two to three years
that is the program we have right now and then MOEA SME administration so for
SME loan programs we have opportunity of equal opportunities principles and
also gender equality principles so we offer a fair financing program to SME
owners according to our number the women account for 30% of these loan programs
and then as of ever since 2024 according to the government white paper
of SMEs that 37% of SMEs owners are women and that is quite in part to the
previous statistics so women business owners are also benefiting from the
government benefits programs and resources and CIP this is CIP economic
development department and in terms of the women's loan that for CIP we have a
comprehensive development fund for indigenous peoples in Taiwan as of now
49% of these alone applicants are women so it's pretty much like 50-50 compared
to men and then the accumulated loan amount women is 3.2 billion and men is
4 billion so there is a 0.5 million of difference but most of the women they
get the loan for consumption and then for men it's usually for women it's
usually for spending and for men it's usually for business starting purposes
and for credit guarantee we do make sure that women can have equal access
and also for these indigenous land reservation loan credit guarantees we
also have three indigenous women apply for these loans any other additional
FSC and then for different loan benefits that FSC in principle would ask all the
financial institutions to work actively with all the competent authorities when
it comes to policy loans and for those in need thank you then lastly we would
like to ask the competent authority to talk about a gender responsive
procurement for the gender budgeting procurement policy or affirmation
procurement so now Taiwan is the government GPA and government procurement
act GPL is the two laws applicable so the basic spirit is to make it fair open
and transparent and then unless the procurement involves national security
otherwise when it comes to the procurement criteria or eligibility we
should not have rules that are not in favor of certain groups and at the
disadvantage of certain vendors therefore we don't have a gender budget
system but in order to realize the spirit of CEDAW and the spirit and value
of gender equality we actually have a lot of supported measures in place for
example when it comes to the tender tender evaluation we actually design a
CSR a mechanism which mentioned in particular that in order to build a
gender inclusive environment we do provide special weightage and in
addition to that in the tender reviewing board in the talent pool for the review
board in business category and the STEM category that women's experts and
scholars do take account for certain percentage however for medical kind of
category or engineer kind of category I think we still have low participation of
women committee members so we are still developing a series of initiatives to
encourage the rise of these female experts participation in the review
process and also for government procurement when it comes to the
certification we also factor in gender issues and gender issues will be part of
the certification process and therefore with all these supportive measures in
2025 when it comes to the business registration all the tender companies we
have all together around a hundred fourteen thousand cases and among them
we have a so we actually have the female female entrepreneur owners winning
28 percent of the total tender fitting so that is the data so we actually see
growth by 0.1 percent so we are seeing a positive trend there thank you and
lastly I would like to come back to answer the first question about the
gender-inclusive facilities especially restrooms a ministry of education do you
have additional information to offer this is ministry of education additional
information here that for these on-campus gender-inclusive facilities in
2022 we have a guideline for gender-inclusive facilities in the
campus and for the gender-inclusive facilities we also offer a manuals for
school to follow and when it comes to helping schools to improve their old
restroom facilities we did ask them to make sure that they are going to build
gender-inclusive facilities and for each one of the building on campus college
campus they have to at least have one gender include more than one gender
inclusive restrooms and then for the is the same for the elementary schools as
well so I think we cover pretty much all the questions and then for other
agencies or ministries do you have any other additional information to offer
here if none then for article 13 I think we can conclude the time here so I'm
going to give the time back to our review committee thank you very much for
the array of responses I'm not sure my colleagues have a follow-up I do
because I think it's important to elaborate on the public or the
government procurement globally that's a market that is worth 13 trillion
dollars in Taiwan your government procurement is worth a hundred billion
dollars annually and the question of affirmative procurement is something
that should be of concern I appreciate that you have government procurement
act but are there any concessions quotas for women owned businesses gender
positive businesses those things I'm not sure included in the current
procurement law and so the need for a gender responsive procurement policy or
mechanism is found to be an economic empowerment pathway to breach
inequalities particularly in the area of social and economic benefits and so I
think it's it's a suggestion that we will be put into you I know that I'm
not sure maybe others heard it but I didn't hear in particular how you were
ensuring that the procurement public procurement including private sector
procurement becomes a social inclusion tool that enables wealth redistribution
within the society by ensuring that procurement market is not is not
manipulated you know there's no monopoly of one sex over the other and I heard a
response about access to financing and and that's women SMEs are given a credit
it would be good to know the percentage that really goes to businesses at the
different levels you had a bulk some and you said about 50% goes to women is it
in all sectors including in infrastructure route construction
housing or is it just for manufacturing and trade and the third area that I had
a concern was women take the credit but for personal development so I don't
understand how that works out that you can actually draw down a loan for
personal development is it for business is it for startups scale up expansion or
I think it would be good to have that kind of insight because it doesn't the
picture is not clear for me that there's access to credit but for men it is used
for business or for women it is used for personal consumption we're not talking
about pensions because pensions are a different ballgame so maybe I didn't
understand well or what was being communicated it didn't really come
across as we're understanding the same thing so those areas I would appreciate
a little clarity and I also didn't hear anything about investment in sports I
thought as a social investment strategy the participation of boys and girls
women and men would be given equal consideration in infrastructure
recruitment coaching and it would be good to hear from the delegation if you
have a strategy as a country to ensure that sports and recreation is beneficial
to you know all regardless of their sex or their location including in the
rural areas I would be keen to know that and I don't know if you have any other
questions to add thank you thank you madam chair yes I'd just like to say
that I was encouraged to hear the responses by the Taiwan in regard to
its attention to the care economy and trying I mean seeing it as as
fundamental to women's human rights in in in achieving gender equality looking
at it paying attention to it transforming the care economy as essential
to women's human rights it occurred to me that the attention that you're
paying to it in providing the public services that that women through the
unpaid care have traditionally provided is is is a pathway forward to addressing
the matter and also the parental leave that you spoke about that is in part
trying to address the issue of redistribution of care within within the
units and so I'm also further encouraging Taiwan to really again really
give this the kind of attention that it needs in terms of transforming the care
economy and and women's lives and and advancement in careers etc financial
independence because this is a part of life that that women contribute to in
creating the capabilities for human beings to survive and to and to grow and
develop and so the kind of attention that the state party ought to give to
this is is immeasurable in terms of the dividends for the country the other area
is the is the tax regime and I really focus on the the consumption tax of that
which I heard the state party say it's not targeting women as such but the the
fact is that it impacts women more than it impacts men and so I'm urging again
that Taiwan to to look at this issue of of that as a regressive tax that and to
find to consider finding other ways to to raise revenue that doesn't impact
women's lives in the way that the vat consumption tax does in fact do and so
I thank you for your responses to to the questions thank you very much now we
will turn back to the delegation but just to augment what one of my colleagues
said is to give you a global picture a few countries have actually started
computing their care economy and you would be delighted or maybe it would
please you to know that the United States has been one of those in the
lead and their annual care economy is worth 1.1 trillion dollars that's the
equivalent of about 30 million hours of regular work so that you can actually
understand this valuation of work that the work that is done in this sector
often not calculated not reflected in your national accounting system but if
you were to actually pay for it would be equivalent to like 30 million people at
the United States earning an income so that that helps for you to know the
value of what you're investing in when you have all of these different programs
and schemes that augment or that try to provide care or to compensate and
subsidize the care that is given to sustain your human capital base because
without that human capital all of your sectors you know rest on it and so it's
worth investing in calculating it because it then helps you to project
your growth and to know what happens when people fall ill when people don't
have the skills what which sectors will be affected so that you can better
position your country and your economy that that's the that's the main goal
because it's often overlooked and I am also delighted that Taiwan is paying
attention to it but I think the reasoning the reason and the rationale
needs to be clear and particularly for those who engage with government they
need to know that it's not asking government to give subsidies it's for
you to enrich and invest in sustaining the base of your economy and on this I
will turn back to the head of the delegation because I believe you might
have some responses to some of the other issues that we raised thank you
thank you very much first of all we would like to thank the true to
reviewers for following up on the clarification and giving us the context
of care economy and we hope that our agencies of the state party when you are
addressing the care economy you can take into consideration some of the context
that have been provided and some of the systems that can be compared because it
sounds like there weren't a lot of follow-up questions it was mainly
suggestions and also contexts given by the reviewers if any of our agencies
would like to further respond I think first of all we can invite the agency
engineering to talk to give us a further update on any preferential or
anything response any preferential treatment for women in terms of
procurement and then we will ask the Ministry of Labor economy and the
indigenous peoples to talk about the various sectors and in terms of the
sports we would like to invite the Ministry of Sports to talk about women
participation in sports field that we start from the public construction
Commission this is the public construction Commission first of all
regarding the government procurement which involves gender budgeting
currently we in our procurement Act we don't have any special treatment for any
single gender and so far in government procurement whether it's public
labor procurement or any kind of procurement if you are facing if you are
reaching a certain volume then it must be limited in under the structure of
the WHO government procurement agreement which is GPA and in GPA there is
no regulation regarding gender procurement now because we have to
fulfill a certain threshold and we must comply with the government procurement
regulations so if we want to overcome the budget issue for gender procurement
then we need to look back into the WTO GPA now regarding credit and financing
we would like to invite Ministry of Labor Council of Indigenous Peoples and
FSC to answer the Ministry of Labor here we have a microfinancing program for the
Phoenix microbusiness startup loan for women and because it's microbusiness so
it's for wholesale hospitality and beauty sectors that employ people less
than employ less than five people and the credit loan rate is 75% for women and
now in terms of the SME office for Ministry of Economic Affairs the reviewers
were more concerned about the credit loan rate for female and what are the main
sectors according to statistics the SME female SME entrepreneurs focus more on
the service sectors and in terms of the service sectors it's the retail wholesale
and retail and the ratio of financing rate we don't have the numbers with us
maybe we can provide you with the numbers next time and in terms of our
office we have a female startup swallow program which guides these women to
guides these women through the different stages of their startup for example when
they first start up we provide them with trainings and consultation for the
startup and if there are a startup within eight years we match them with
accelerators and international accelerators for interaction and exchanges
and we also have elite screenings for female there are also assistance and
guidance for business and startup model business models so we don't have the
numbers of the loans provided to female entrepreneurs but we help them to
obtain these fundings and finances thank you very much we can have the Department
of Gender Equality to say if the Ministry of Economy is going to provide further
document or figures can you provide it to us before 630 today it's a bit can we
do that before 10 tomorrow morning okay we'll do it before 10 tomorrow now
Council of Indigenous Peoples from the comprehensive development fund that's
been started for indigenous loans as of yesterday we have three over three
thousand nine hundred loans for a male and the ratio over 1.1 billion and the
female ratio is the ratio is fifty three point seven the female loan is are the
over three thousand with a little over 0.9 billion the ratio is forty six point
twenty six so we can see it's comparable in terms of credit loans for the credit
loans the percentage is fifty percent fifty fifty percent for indigenous loans
that's about financing FSC do you have anything to add here at FSC here like we
mentioned earlier Ron regarding the finance the financing programs provided
by various agencies and ministries we are we encourage financial institutions
to provide these loans and it's developed according to the market
strategy we also ask the banking union to assist female loan measures and the
information are published on the website
we don't have the Ministry of Sports here so the Department of Gender Equality
will explain on behalf of the Ministry of Sports according to the Ministry of
they have the statistics for female athletes in 2023 that's thirty one point
five percent that's lower than the male which is thirty eight point seven and
because of this gender gap we also notice that it's because there is a
lower regular as exercise rate and including these consideration for the
exercise environment and also the duty of pressure for taking care of the
family and in the future we should provide more facilities and environment
that's more friendly to women to improve women's sports participation and from
twenty twenty six to twenty twenty nine our important issues that's going to be
focused on by the executive when we asked Ministry of Sports to add KPIs
regarding female athletes or female exercise rate we hope that the female
regular exercising rate can be increased by zero point five percent per year and
we hope that the Ministry of Sports and relevant agencies can develop policies
and programs to promote sports responding to the corresponding to
different genders and we hope that in the future there can be gender-friendly
considerations placed in all venues and thank you about this gender and sports
issue anything from Ministry of Education I know maybe you don't have to
respond to the sports part but you can actually talk about the gender equality
part as for the PE classes so far we are actually working together with a
Ministry of Sports and there will be a division of responsibilities in terms of
the measures to encourage physical activities for female students we are
still going to drive toward to the goal of gender equality thank you for a care
economy do we have additional information from other colleagues here
from our delegation with regard to care economy if none then so the follow-up
questions do we have any other information for that if none then I'm
going to give the time back to our review committee thank you
much head of delegation for the rich response and we can see the
collaboration across entities to be able to address some of these emerging
issues and intersecting concerns linking the economy with sports with procurement
we appreciate it we do not take it for granted we will now move on to article
14 and I will now yield the floor to Professor Leticia.
Thank you.
Thank you, Chair.
Okay, the state party reports than the economic conditions of the indigenous
population remain relatively disadvantages with income significantly
lower than the national average.
Please provide updated information on measures taken to address economic
inequalities affecting rural and indigenous women.
The state party indicates that that indigenous populations are increasingly
moving to urban areas and that housing ownership remains lower than the
national average.
Please explain how policies address structural disadvantages
faced by rural women including access to land and housing.
Please indicate what measures are taken to ensure rural women access to
digital technologies.
Please provide information on access to health care education and social
services for rural women including regional disparities.
Taiwan has a high proportion of elderly people.
What's being done regarding health care and social security for older women?
Are there specific programs in place?
Are there policies for the economic autonomy of women with disabilities
and for implementation of reasonable accommodation useful for their daily
life?
And lastly, are there programs to the care of women deprived of their
liberty?
What's being done to meet their basic needs, particularly medical care
tailored to their specific requirements?
Thank you, Chair.
Thank you.
It seems that we can actually ask CIP to answer the question and then after
CIP then I think a lot of these questions have to do with the work of Ministry
of Health and Welfare, especially relevant to long-term care.
So we would like to ask colleagues from Ministry of Health and Welfare to
answer that and also the Ministry of Agriculture.
Can you also answer the question because the question, especially the
question concerning a rural area women.
So we would like to ask a Ministry of Agriculture to also chip in later so
we can start first with the IP Council of Indigenous Peoples.
This is the Director General of Development Department for Indigenous
Economy.
So the Economic Development Department will answer the question and also
the Social Welfare Department will talk about employment and for the
Social Service Department, they were not notified to join this meeting.
Therefore, for the question with regard to housing, probably we can only
give you very brief answer for Indigenous economic development.
We have industry development programs over the years.
We also have programs set aside for Indigenous women.
For example, the Million Dollar Entrepreneur Award from 2013-16 to 2025
over the course of 10 years, we have taken 215 cases and proposals.
So 85 of them were applied by women and for other different programs,
for example, industry development featuring rural characteristics,
we have different industrial programs to train and support them.
That is for industry economy empowerment and for the housing.
I know that Ministry of Interior are providing social building.
They work together with local governments to support their housing
and induce people, their percentage of being awarded social housing has
already exceeded that proportion of Indigenous population among the
total national population.
So about the social services provided to Indigenous peoples at CIP,
when it comes to social services, we have nationwide 66 family support
centers for Indigenous peoples.
We have 222 social workers and 33 supervisors working at the
Indigenous Family Support Center and we have 530 Indigenous cultural
and health stations, employee 1,400 caregivers and also in 10 regions
across Taiwan, we have Indigenous employment service offices employing
around 77 full-time staff.
Therefore, altogether, we have 1,480 full-time employees providing
and supporting these programs and organizations and women account
for around 62%, which means that for all the Indigenous social welfare
area, the staff, their gender, the majority of them are very much women.
So that's the information I have.
Any other information from CIP?
If none, I think for Indigenous peoples and also the rural women,
I think we would like to ask Ministry of Agriculture to answer the
question first and then we ask the Ministry of Education to talk about
your programs to bridge the gap of digital divide.
So we actually have a lot of areas concerning long-term care.
So we would like to ask Ministry of Health to provide your information
later.
So first, from Ministry of Agriculture for rural women, we provide
education and training programs.
For example, we have this Tianma branch restaurants and then also for
the rural community talent programs, we all have relevant trainings.
So maybe we can ask another administration, the rural administration,
additional information here.
In order to support rural women's employment and economy empowerment,
we have this brand.
It's called the Tianma, Mother Tian.
It's actually chain restaurants.
They actually offer these local sourced cuisines and also food products
featuring the local ingredients and they can also combine the local tourism
to increase local employment and job opportunities at the same time to
provide more economic opportunities for local people and give them more
economic competitiveness.
And from 2021 to 2024 for these Tianma, Mother restaurants programs,
we have trained altogether 1,800 people and women account for a very
high percentage by 1,354 women.
And then in terms of the rural area talent development programs, when it
comes to local indigenous, sorry, local industry development or local
cultural preservation and revitalization of communities, when it comes
to training criteria, we are open to anyone, everyone.
Therefore, we do not distinguish between different genders.
And for all the, but we do secure training programs and resources for
women.
So the total people receiving the training among them, the women account
for 54.7%.
Therefore, we do see there is a parity there.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Michi of agriculture.
It seems we also talk about social housing before.
See IP you talk about social housing.
Maybe we can ask the Ministry of Interior colleague to elaborate more
on that.
So this is the Homeland Administration.
So the CIP talking I mentioned about the social housing for indigenous
peoples living in rural area, sorry in urban area.
So as of June of 2026 indigenous people with social housing.
Uh, we have a total number of 2855 how indigenous households getting
living in the social housing.
So they account for 10% of social housing occupancy.
And then for the overall, uh, so women account for 55.5% for leasing
of the social housing and any other information on indigenous
areas or rural areas.
If none, then we are going now to keep floor to Ministry of Health
and Welfare.
So for a Ministry of Health and Welfare, so about indigenous area
and rural area, women's access to health care in addition to offer
a citizen over age over 65 and induce people over 55.
We offer them a vaccination programs and also we would ensure that
we pervade sufficient health care, manpower to localize medical
services.
And also we work together with the local clinic centers in townships
in indigenous regions.
And we have support care for 3800 indigenous woman and 2100 of them
are aged person over 65 years old.
And also for indigenous women, we also provide them subsidiaries
and benefits for prenatal checkups and medical access to medical
services.
And then we have provided this subsidy up to 16,000 people.
And then also we have these the indigenous people's Health Policy
Council.
So these Council the board members include 50% of them are indigenous
persons and then also over a third of them are female and we are
actually working on a program for 2026 to 2030.
So it's a long-term program covering sub 16 projects which include
long-term care project for indigenous communities, long-term
care resource support network so they can actually age in place so
we can also ensure there is a cultural sensitive and safe care
deliver to indigenous communities and for Ministry of Health with
regard to indigenous peoples including people living with disabilities
the social welfare benefits.
So according to the law now once they have these disability
certificate and then that we have the case handlers.
It would actually conduct a phone interviews to or to visit in person
to understand their service needs and then they will refer them to
the proper service units so they can have access to the benefits
they need including economic benefits or community-based facility
service as for elders in different parts of Taiwan.
We also have community care centers in different regions to support
our elders and there are actually this is in person and care phone
calls and also a food and meal delivery services and based on
their different local cultures.
We will provide different services accordingly.
I would also like to add the reasonable accommodation in terms of
our act for the protection of persons with disabilities.
We've already included reasonable accommodation in our amendments
and it's pending in legislative here for adoption.
Thank you very much Ministry of Health and welfare.
Would you like to follow up if not?
I think I forgot about Ministry of Education that's supposed to
answer about digital gap.
We are at the information and technology office here.
We have four digital developments that are in the second or fourth
tier.
We have digital opportunity centers.
There are currently 104 centers to narrow the remote and rural area
female education and digital capability gap from 2024 to
2026.
We have trained over 50,000 people among which for over 40,000
42,000 are females.
Trainees it's about 30 77.16% and we also hosted 307 seminars
for the training courses to improve their digital capability.
We also have data here.
We have female local development program that's provided by NSC
and MOEA.
This is MSC in terms of local development.
We have regional revitalization.
We have youth empowerment workstations and relevant rewards
for these and subsidies for these troops in for the youth
empowerment workstations.
If they are there for station there for five years and they
are more experienced they can assist local youth to work on
local issues including employment or develop local cultures
as of 2025 in our over 130 state workstations.
There are about not 49 workstations that are led by women
and according to these numbers we have over 4700 people who
have been trained in these 49 workstations and in our four
year mid long-term program we've also stipulated that there
must be 40% of female participation in the program and
currently we have about 38%.
Thank you.
MOEA would you like to add anything?
Yes.
Thank you very much.
We are the office of Bureau of MOEA SME startup.
We work with NSC in providing a program for regional development
and we take inventory of local DNAs as core for our SME
development and startup and to come up and develop feature
products.
We also have mentorship and counseling in which if you have
female participation it's a plus and we also introduce gender
equality perspectives to reinforce female participation
and employment from 2021 to 2024 in all of the cases that
we've counseled and guided.
Female project chairs take up about 39% and female ownership
is about 50% and in terms of newly added employment female
employment adds about takes up about 60% so overall the stable
employment for female is about 60%.
We can see that the numbers prove our policy has substantially
facilitate the participation of female in the economy and in
terms of female empowerment and regional development we focus
on digital marketing product development brand management
and product production and management and we focus on local
women and home returning youth.
Thank you very much reviewers for all of your questions.
We would like to know if any of our agencies or ministries
have anything to add.
If not, we now give the floor back to our reviewers.
Thank you.
Thank you very very much.
I think you gave us an array of questions before we move on.
I would just want a little clarification.
You talked about the beneficiaries.
I heard the agency for digital regional development talking
about digital financing.
I was just curious about the issue of digital governance and
gender equality because the data that we have which I cited
yesterday is that less than 13% of the governance of tech
companies is led by women and the management of technology
industries and that's a huge, you know, because Taiwan
occupies a unique and strategic space in the evolving digital
economy where you are providing over 60% of imputes
and hardware that is the backbone for the digital economy
for the whole world.
But in that sector, governance within that sector is skewed.
And so what plans do you have to ensure that digital governance
and the rules about internal policies and recruiting and the
vision and products in the digital sector are inclusive and
that women really have a place around the table to shape the
direction of the new economy?
If it's possible to get that answer, if there's a plan or it's
something you're noting or it's something that you want to work
on, it will be interesting to know because that is an area
that is creating new forms of inequalities in how the digital
economy is being designed, shaped and the trends and some of
it is reinventing discrimination and we would really want to
know what your plan is.
Thank you.
I think this is a question we're going to ask Moda to take up.
If any other agencies would like to follow up, feel free later
on.
Thank you very much for your question.
Today, our colleagues present does not include any one in
digital development.
We will respond in writing by 10 tomorrow morning.
Thank you.
Can we, Madame Chair, do you agree that we provide you a
response in writing by 10 tomorrow morning because we don't
have the colleagues here with us today?
With pleasure, Honorable Minister.
Thank you very much for accommodating that.
I know we've had very, very good responses and I believe that
the commitment that the government of Taiwan has shown and
if there's no benchmarks in place already, I'm sure even this
interaction will trigger for you to begin to work on it and
have targets in terms of digital inclusion in digital governance.
I think this brings us to the end of Article 13 and 14.
I believe we could take a little coffee break and health break
and then we can come back to consider Article 15 and 16.
Thank you very much.
Madame Chair, should we do, according to the schedule, 15
minute break or 3 45?
It would be because we end the session five minutes earlier.
So should we do with 15 minutes or 20 minutes stick to the
schedule? 15 minutes.
15 minutes.
Okay, then we'll take a 15 minute break.
So we originally set the time to come back at 3 45.
But now it's 3 25.
So it's 3 40.
3 40.
When we return to the venue, we'll continue to review 15
and 16.
We'll take a 15 minute break and we'll be back by 3 40 for
the review of articles 15 and 16.
Thank you.
I would like to remind all parties that if you would like to submit your
information, you can submit your information before 6.30 today.
If it's too late, we can submit it before 10 a.m. tomorrow.
Thank you for your cooperation.
Please prepare seven English versions and two Chinese versions when you submit your information.
Thank you.
Okay, we'll begin in about five minutes.
Everybody please take your seats for the next session for the review of articles 15 and 16.
Okay, we're about to begin the next session for the review of articles 15 and 16.
If we finish this session early, the meeting with the non-governmental organizations will begin in advance.
Please get ready for it.
Okay, welcome back. We now move on to the review of articles 15 and 16.
And now to begin back to Madam Chair.
Thank you very much and welcome back from the health break.
I will now yield the floor to Professor Heisushin to take article 15 and 16.
You have the floor, Prof.
Thank you, Madam Chair.
Article 15 is about women's equality with men before the law.
In civil matters, women's legal capacity, same as men's, and then same opportunities to exercise that capacity,
equal rights to conclude contracts and to administer property, etc.
Under article 15, I would like to raise only one issue,
which was raised before, and that is ancestor worship guilds.
In 2022, the international review committee recommended that
the government needs to revise the proposed amendment to the Act for
Ancestor Worship Guild and apply the gender equality principle retroactively
so that it covers all guilds, including those that were formed before 2008.
And the government report says that at the end of 2022,
there were about 3,200 ancestor worship guilds.
The exact number was 3,244, out of which
691 established regulations before the Act was promulgated,
which is corresponding to 21.3% of the total guilds.
And then in 2023, there was a constitutional court ruling that it is unconstitutional.
So I would like to ask the government what's the current situation regarding ensuring gender equality
for all ancestor worship guilds, whether they have their own regulation or not,
or whether the guilds was formed before 2008 or not, and I think there were some loopholes
so that some ancestor worship guilds can get away from this requirement.
So may I have the reply? What is the current status?
Are all ancestor worship guilds guarantee equality,
no matter whether they already gave out certificate only to the male members?
And how do you apply the principle of gender equality so that all ancestor worship guilds
have this same equality guaranteed for its woman members?
So that would be my question regarding Article 15. Thank you.
Thank you. So the floor is now to the delegation to respond to that question for Article 15.
Thank you for that question. For the ancestor worship guilds, which was interpreted already at the constitutional court,
I think the Ministry of Interior should take this question, and other ministries can also answer the question.
So here, for the religious and ritual agency, this ancestor worship guilds is actually
an independent property organization set up for the worship of ancestors.
So ever since that act, all the offsprings should all become this core worshippers,
and then also gender equality principle should apply, especially for the membership.
And also in 2023, the constitutional court ruling, it was ruled that the women offsprings also enjoyed the same benefits.
Therefore, we have drafted an act governing ancestral worship guilds.
So for these direct offsprings, regardless of their gender, they should all be listed as members, or they have these inheritance rights.
Therefore, in the future, for all these ancestral worship guilds, they should not exclude female offsprings.
So all these offsprings, regardless of their gender, can all become the members.
And then also the 691, those were the guilds that established beforehand.
So their rules only stipulate that the male can become the member.
So for Zhishui Yuan, do we have the civil court?
Can also because it's not just about the worship rights, it's also about the property rights.
So for these worship guilds, that in terms of the gender equality disputes,
that we also have these constitutional court ruling.
And so for the article 4.1 and point 2, that the act governing ancestral worship guilds,
this is unconstitutional because it excludes female offspring.
So for these relevant articles, I think we need to follow the draft of Ministry of Interior,
and then we can offer our interpretation of that. Thank you.
So any other agency would like to provide additional information,
then if not, we are going to give the floor back to our review committee. Thank you.
Can I ask you then, so these 691 ancestral worship guilds,
which were formed before, can the female members that belong to those guilds
can bring a lawsuit and then claim the same equal rights after this constitutional court ruling?
The lawsuit should be brought by individual members if they found that they want to have the equal rights.
Should they wait for the Ministry of Interior's interpretation,
or can you apply this constitutional court ruling retroactively,
no matter when the guilds were formed, and then female members can be guaranteed the same right
in terms of property division, in terms of whatever membership or attendance and participation?
That would be my question.
So the Ministry of Interior, can you offer an answer to that?
Can they actually use the constitutional ruling as the basis to file lawsuits?
So I think the Ministry of, I think Judicial Yuan probably also have an answer.
We would like to ask the Ministry of Interior to answer first.
Yes, so Ministry of Interior additional information here.
So, so far, for those ancestral worship guilds that have rules,
only a male offspring can become a member, and according to the constitutional court interpretation,
that rules, so that membership rules have already been ruled by the constitutional court.
So we do have a principle, so for those, the rules that only stipulate,
that only male line can inherit the property and the rights.
And for the moment, and once the draft new rule, and it's adopted,
and then after we amend the law, then still the membership rights to the worship guilds,
regardless of their genders, if the draft law is adopted, then they can actually assume their rights,
which means that if their regulation do not say that only male can inherit the rights,
therefore according to the constitutional court, then a female offspring can also ask for the membership.
So that is the answer from Ministry of Interior.
And then the Judicial Yuan, can you actually add on, do you have different interpretation for that?
Okay, so for Judicial Yuan, with regard to the current article 4.1 of Act Governing Ancestral Worship Guilds,
so these, before the act interpretation, we have two situations.
So if this guild's already established, and then they also have their own internal rules,
and because there is a free spirit of contracting contracts,
therefore according to the constitution, then that rule still stands.
And then for those ancestral worship guilds that still exist,
if they don't have internal rules before the constitutional interpretation,
therefore according to the constitutional interpretation, in this scenario,
that there is a violation of gender equality, and in this scenario,
then these ancestral worship guilds, their female offspring can actually assume the rights of membership.
So in current situation, if they don't have internal rule,
and then also according to the constitutional court, they can actually make that claim to the right.
So basically that is the same, like the Ministry of Interior,
if there are internal rules and then there are no internal rules, then we can follow the rules.
Any other question? If none, then we can give the floor back to the review committee.
What do you do? How do you ensure gender equality in case there is already internal regulation made?
And then the constitutional court ruling guarantees gender equality,
but still Judicial Yuan says that in case there was internal regulation,
the original only male rights will stay.
So there is no overturning of that situation.
And that is a loophole, that is a vacuum where you need to amend.
And then you said that if the draft law is adopted,
but what is the government plan to amend the law and what is the timeline to do that?
So that would be my two questions.
So in your draft law, you want to change that situation regarding those skills
which already had internal regulation, which gives rights only to the male members, right?
Can you clarify?
I think we will invite Ministry of Interior to elaborate on how your revised regulations are
regarding these internal regulations of the guilds.
So this is the MOI.
According to our guild's draft and the process of our review,
in 2023 it's reviewed by the Executive Yuan, it's now sent to the Legislative Yuan.
Currently the draft is sitting at the Executive Yuan.
And as I said earlier in our Article 4, it says it excludes the internal regulations.
After the amendments are completed, we do not consider the internal regulations.
There is an equality of gender.
If you are a direct descendant and you all bear the duty of worship, then you can all enjoy membership.
The draft is currently sitting at the Executive Yuan.
And the Executive Yuan reminds us to talk to the guilds.
And we've talked to them.
All of their opinions will be included in our draft for review or improvement.
Which means that the draft is currently sitting at the Executive Yuan
and it could possibly be further amended pending your dialogue with the guilds.
Yes, we will have to wait for consensus to be built for us to further amend it.
And maybe if there are different opinions to the amendment, basically we will follow the constitutional ruling.
Thank you.
So we have further elaborated on this question.
Maybe there are still different opinions in the society and they haven't been brought together.
So we do need further communication in the society.
But basically we will follow the direction of the constitutional ruling.
So in the future, even if they still have internal regulations, gender equality is still the main consideration.
So I now give the floor back to our reviewers.
Thank you for the clarification.
And in that case, I would only ask the government to expedite the process of adopting the amendment,
the revision of the act for this ancestral worship guilds, please.
Because it was previous recommendation already.
And clearly for the next review in four years later, 2030 I think,
by that time you should be finished it all already.
Hopefully next year.
So thank you very much.
I think we will continue with you, Professor Hesu, unless there's any additional comments, questions?
None?
Now to Article 16.
You have the floor, please.
Okay.
So I will continue to raise issues under Article 16.
Article 16 is regarding marriage and family.
The same right for women at the time of marriage and during marriage,
and at the time of divorce or separation, at the dissolution of marriage.
In this case, there is also a need to speed up the legislative implementation regarding the Constitutional Court judgment number four of 2023.
And then to realize this, I would like to raise three issues under this Article 16
in relation to divorce.
First is the question regarding division of residual marital property.
The division of marital property continues to vary by occupation.
That was already raised in our list of issues.
And then you know that the division of marital property does not apply to all people with different occupations.
So my question is, how is the government going to ensure that pensions across all occupational sectors are included
within the scope of claims for the division of residual marital property?
So that's the first question.
If I can use the example of my own country, in my country nowadays what we call sunset divorce is increasing.
So people, especially women, after the age of 60, after the marital years of more than 30 years,
they want to get divorced because they want to live their own free life, not under the patriarchal husband anymore.
So the sunset divorce, what we term sunset divorce, is increasing.
And then, of course, this issue of division of national pension, how it should be divided among the couples.
So I think it is not exactly the same, but at the time of divorce,
how the property is divided, including pensions, is very important for the economic security of women, especially in later years.
So that would be my question.
How the division of residual marital property includes all types of occupations,
regardless of the pensions, whether it is farmers or laborers.
You have only provided the division in terms of civil servants, teachers, and military personnel, and not included others.
So that would be my question.
My second question is regarding alimony.
The executive UN has proposed amendments to expand eligibility by adding,
and I quote the wording, reduced earning capacity or
reduced employment opportunities at the time of divorce as a condition to request alimony.
But also proposed provisions terminating the right to claim alimony upon remarriage.
So we have already discussed this issue a lot in the morning as well as yesterday somewhat.
Because women are the main bearers of family responsibilities in terms of housework,
child rearing, care for the elderly, if there is a child with disability.
The burden is on women primarily,
which result in reduced earning capacity or reduced employment opportunities for women.
So the requirements for alimony should take this into account and
be relaxed because women are the main carers for the family.
However, this claim for alimony should not be connected whether the divorced woman would remarry or not.
It has nothing to do with it.
So how is this proposed amendment going to do it regarding alimony?
But how about your deletion of this connection of alimony if a divorced woman would remarry?
So that would be my second question.
And third question under this article 16 would be the issue of mediation in case of divorce.
You have divorce through litigation, but also you have divorce through mediation.
And mediation for divorce in case of domestic violence especially needs special attention,
because women want to get out of this violent situation and want divorce.
And then because a woman might want to get divorced as soon as possible,
rather than litigation in a legal process which takes longer,
she might want to go a more speedy way of mediation.
And then I have the information that in some cases the mediators request
or ask women to drop the charges for protection orders, which should not happen.
So I would like to know what kind of measures you are taking
to make sure that that kind of demand or request or force or urge
does not happen to women to drop the protection order.
And then whether you are thinking of ways to ensure that mediators have this gender perspective
and understand the nature of domestic violence.
And of course I know that in Taiwan the majority of divorce happens through agreement,
consent by both parties without going through mediation, without going through the legal procedure.
But still about 13% is through these procedures, either mediation or legal procedures.
So how do you deal with these cases of divorce, especially in terms of domestic violence?
I saw in my country there are even cases of killing in the court room.
And while they were waiting for their turn to be counseled,
the husband was hiding a knife and then killed the wife.
Because of course in times of divorce all the tension and aggravation escalates.
So there should be precautions, measures, especially when domestic violence is involved.
So that would be my three questions regarding policies in Taiwan.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Do you have any other questions to add?
So we will use that to the dedicate.
Thank you very much.
These three questions have to do with the legal departments and justice departments.
So we're going to have the Ministry of Justice to answer the first question.
And then the Department of Gender Equality will talk about residual asset division.
And for the alimony, the Ministry of Justice will elaborate, followed by the Judicial Yuan.
And finally, about the mediation of divorce and involving domestic violence,
we will have the Judicial Yuan elaborate.
And of course, if the Ministry of Justice can answer the third question, feel free to jump in.
This is from the Ministry of Justice.
Regarding the question of the residual marital property and inclusion of pensions,
according to our current regulations in the 1013 article of the Civil Code,
it states the request of residual marital property, whether or not to include the pensions,
because previously when we were taking an inventory of the pensions,
we realized that different occupations have different standards of calculating the pension.
So we need to go back to the various calculation of the respective occupation.
And we had the Executive Yuan invite cross-department discussion.
And finally, it was decided that the resolution was made that various occupation pension
competent authorities should amend their respective clauses to include pension in their residual property division.
And the other sectors are working on it as well.
So Department of Gender Equality for Divorced Women, their financial security,
is actually a great important topic for us at the Executive Yuan.
So in 2022, we asked the Judicial Yuan to conduct a research into the fairness for divorced spouse economic fairness research.
And we also have relevant meetings.
Since 2023, with regard to this division of occupational depensions,
we also have inter-ministrial meetings.
And when it comes to the military and civil service and educators and also the civil servants,
they have individual pension regulations.
And then for those occupational pensions that are not yet included in those like industrial pension rules,
then we have these Ministry of Transportation, Ministry of Economic Affairs,
and central banks to actually factor in those division of pension respectively.
And because there are different regulations and different reciprocal principles,
and then we actually need to ask the competent authorities to apply according to the actual situation in practice.
So there are negotiations needed.
Therefore, Executive Yuan would actually ask the competent authorities to continuously consult experts to build consensus in the society.
Additional information here.
So for different occupational pensions, like you mentioned, different ministries,
they are already making progress on any other draft revisions for these respective pension systems.
If none, okay, let's move on to the second question.
So about alimony, about the alimony revision of law, we would like to ask the Ministry of Justice to take that question.
So second time making comments from the Ministry of Justice, so about the alimony.
So the current Civil Code Article 1057 and then for the alimony claim due to financial difficulties for make a living.
So last year we actually have this draft revision that also the difficulty of living can be the basis for the claim of alimony.
And then also because of the marriage and then the damage to the career development opportunities,
that is also part of the legal basis for the claim for alimony.
So now the Legislative Yuan is now deliberating on this revision of law.
And then also the first review meeting was conducted in April this year at Legislative Yuan.
And so they are now actively reviewing this draft as for the cancellation of alimony because of remarriage.
So we actually refer to many of the other countries' legislations.
So it's quite universally that if one part of the spouse remarry,
and because they are going to build a new family relationship with a new spouse,
and then they are going to support each other in that new relationship to avoid the difficulty and complexity of calculation of the alimony.
So most of the other countries we refer to usually would actually make this remarriage as one of the legal basis of canceling the alimony.
Therefore, we also include that in our draft.
So that's our answer.
Thank you very much.
Any additional information to the second question?
So this is the domestic court representative.
So for the alimony and the civil code revision,
because of the alimony claim on the basis of the losing job opportunities because of marriage, actually we do agree with that.
So we are just working on the wordings for technicality.
So actually, in general principle, we support that.
And then in terms of remarriage, leading to the cancellation of alimony because of remarriage.
So because the Jewish Ministry of Justice is actually a competent authority,
we respect that indeed after this remarriage,
the alimony claim would continue to make the complexity worsening,
and then it's not beneficial for the new relationship maintenance.
And then also the alimony cancellation would actually apply not only to women, but also to men.
And for the residual division of residual marital property,
so for the occupational pension that's have already collected,
it would actually, the article 1030 would apply.
That will be part of the residual marital property.
So the claim, so before for the pension that hasn't make place,
then that would be the part that we are going to have to work on.
So that is the answer to question one and two.
Any other information on alimony?
If none, then we are going to move on to the third question.
Maybe we can ask Zhu Shouyuan to probably give a background overview,
and then other ministries can also offer insights.
So answer three.
So this is the team and also the domestic court representative.
So thank you for the question.
So for the mediation processes when domestic violence involved,
according to Domestic Violence Prevention Act,
in a domestic case, in the procedure, if domestic violence is involved,
in principle, mediation is not allowed.
However, if in the process of the mediation,
if the mediator has received training on DV,
then the mediation can make sure that the victims can be protected.
Then that mediation can be adopted.
So so far we have existing procedures to provide domestic violence training
for domestic mediators, and that will be the core training program,
and also for our domestic affair mediation rules.
And then for these mediators who have already received DV training,
then they will be specifically specified in the list.
Therefore, they will be preferred candidate for domestic affairs mediation.
And also in the procedure, during the procedure of domestic affair mediation,
then we would also have notice which will give the parties relevant
safety evaluation checkpoints.
So if they have any safety and security concerns,
they can actually send us back the form,
and then we will make arrangement accordingly.
For example, we can have the separate interviews,
or we can have these tele-video forms of interview,
so we can avoid further violence being committed.
And also even we would arrange social worker accompanying the whole process.
So in and after the mediation, if the party is not happy with the mediator
and then having concerns about the mediator's professionality,
then also we have evaluation mechanism in place.
They can actually give us the feedback,
and they can submit the feedback in paper copy form,
and they can scan the QR code to submit their feedback
should they have any concern during the mediation process.
If the mediator is not appropriate mediator,
they can actually give the feedback to inform the court.
Then the court also have these evaluation team for the mediators.
Once they receive these kind of complaints,
then they will kickstart investigation process.
And should it be a severe case, if it's a severe violation of mediation rules,
then we would actually dismiss them
and then terminate our contract with the mediators.
So Ministry of Justice or other government representatives
would like to add additional information.
Anyone?
Anyone from Judicial Yuan?
This is the team in the Domestic Affairs Court,
and then also in the mediation process
that the party is required to abandon the injunction protection order.
This has never happened in my own career,
so I think this is probably during the mediation process
when the party agree divorce
and then they're demanding that the victim
to withdraw the application for protection order.
This is quite common.
So I think it's before the protection order is issued,
then since they're going to get a divorce,
they want to see the withdrawal of the protection order application.
So this is something we see in practice.
But we would actually see how it goes in reality
before we actually approve that withdrawal of that protection order application,
because security and safety will be our utmost concern.
That is the priority.
So any other information?
Any other additional information you would like to offer
to the three questions,
or you want to answer these questions respectively?
If none, thank you very much.
Now I'm going to give the floor back to the review committee.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, follow-up questions.
After listening to your replies,
the last issue first, so mediation in case of divorce.
I understand that for domestic affairs cases,
you need to guarantee that there are precautions
and if any dissatisfaction with the mediators,
any complaint, then the woman is going to submit the feedback.
But I guess it's voluntary, right?
It's not mandatory after the couple goes through the mediation.
If they feel they want to provide any feedback, they can.
But you are not for sure collecting all the feedback
or what is the system.
After any mediation process,
then you make sure that you collect feedback always,
or is it voluntary.
So if those women or men who went through the mediation process
and then were fed up, really did not satisfy,
but they might not give their feedback, which still happens.
So I am asking whether it's mandatory requirement
or is it voluntary to submit the feedback.
I can understand that you are trying to collect the response afterwards.
So that's one point.
And then in case of before applying this protection order,
I know that these days some men have a stalking habit,
whether it's a divorced spouse or whether it's in a close relationship
before marriage, stalking happens a lot.
And then that might happen even between divorced couples.
You divorce and then your former spouse is coming after you every day
to your workplace, near your workplace, your new home, etc.,
harassed by the telephone messages, etc.
So there should be precautions after the couple went through the divorce,
whether through litigation or mediation work.
So we need all these precautionary measures.
So in case the woman feels that she needs protection order before,
after divorce, I think that should be given.
So that would be my response for mediation,
especially in case of domestic violence.
And now this issue of alimony.
I think Minister of Justice and Judicial Yuan,
I think both agree that alimony should be canceled after remarriage of the spouse.
And then you said that it applies both to men and women.
Of course, the law should apply to both spouses.
But I think it is disproportionately women who receive alimony,
unless the woman is a rich millionaire.
Usually it is women who are economically weaker and dependent upon the husband.
So alimony applies the effect of cancellation of the alimony.
Of course, it affects women disproportionately.
So this cancellation of alimony, I don't know why you think it's complicated.
And then what countries are you taking into account and studying the case?
Because you said that you are also checking other countries' laws and systems.
So may I ask which countries you are taking the example of
in terms of cancellation of alimony upon remarriage after divorce?
And then the first issue of division of residual marital property.
I know that you are preparing and discussing with different ministries,
different UNs, and then trying to come up with amendments so
that the division of marital property applies to all occupations.
So may I ask what kind of timeline do you have in mind?
How long do you think the whole process would take?
Because that might take ten years if there is no active
measures taken or initiatives taken by the government.
So that would be my response.
And then I would wait for further replies.
Thank you.
So any responses from the delegation?
Regarding these questions, the mediation, we would like to invite elaboration
from the judicial union regarding the protection orders and mediation
and if other ministries have things to elaborate.
For example, stalking also has to do with the Ministry of Justice.
This is about stalking.
Maybe we can invite the Ministry of Justice to follow up.
This is regarding mediation of divorce.
And regarding the cancellation of alimony after remarriage,
earlier on you mentioned that you were looking at other countries as well.
And reviewers would like to know which countries are you looking at.
Maybe the Ministry of Justice can elaborate on this as well.
And finally, about the residual property division and alimony pension,
this will be handled by the Department of Gender Equality.
Thank you for your questions.
This is from the Office of Tribunal and Family Affairs.
Regarding the opinion and feedback from the plaintiff, is it mandatory?
Usually these feedbacks or evaluation checklists would be provided to the
plaintiff in the form of QR code, but in our family court affairs,
the judge will do the final mediation and checking to sign the statement.
So all of the family affairs mediation will be confirmed by the judge if in the process
the plaintiff realizes that they are not, in fact, accepting of the requests made
or the opinions made by the mediator.
The plaintiff can respond to the judge at the end and the judge will personally
chair the mediation to find the best way to mediate it.
And secondly, when it involves the protection order,
if it has to do with stalking and security, safety of the plaintiffs,
in addition to provide, we will send a notification to the plaintiff
so that they will know, they can notify the court that there are concerns of their security
and the court can arrange for quarantine or separation so that there are no danger for them.
And if danger happens within the courts,
there are emergency bells installed in the mediation rooms.
Once the marshals receive any notification,
they will immediately provide assistance in the mediation room.
And if they feel that they are concerned about their safety leaving the court,
the local police can also assist.
Would the judicial, the Ministry of Justice would like to elaborate,
especially in terms of stalking or is it the responsibility of the Ministry of Interior?
Okay, domestic violence falls under the jurisdiction of Ministry of Health and Welfare.
Then we will invite the MOHW.
Thank you very much.
We would like to further elaborate that it was mentioned earlier, Ron,
when the two parties are mediating or in the process of divorce
and in addition to because of domestic violence,
a protection order is filed, applied for,
and if there are stalking issues, according to our Stalking and Harassment Prevention Act,
we can ask police to file a written warning.
And there are also safety plans that can be used.
And there is also an app they can download that will help to locate them.
And the police can know where they are to provide assistance in the case of emergencies.
Thank you very much.
Are there any other agencies who would like to elaborate on this domestic violence and stalking issue?
No?
Then we move on to the second question about alimony.
And we would like to invite the Ministry of Justice to talk about the references they've been looking at.
So we mainly looked at Germany and Switzerland.
Their regulations say that if the other spouse remarries, the alimony will be canceled.
But we must say that our draft is based on the court ruling right now.
If the two parties they negotiate for,
it depends on how the two parties negotiate on the alimony,
or if it's just a one-off alimony payment, then it won't be limited to this.
There will be no cancellation.
And the cancellation is mainly about continuous or regular payments.
Before the new marriage, they can receive the alimony.
And whether or not this, because after remarriage,
it's very difficult for the new spouse and the previous spouses to discuss the allocation of their child raising.
And it's because there is a difficulty in this consideration,
so we have included remarriage as one of the reasons for canceling regular alimony payment.
Okay, are there any other explanations?
If not, we go to the Department of Gender Equality for Residual Property Division.
Now, when we talk about the timeline for the amendment in 2023,
our cross-department consultation,
it was decided that the Occupational Pension Act amendments
will be amended individually by various competent authorities.
And then we will amend them all together.
And they will follow the Retirement Act for Public Servants and refer to the wordings.
Now, this year, we further asked about the amendment for the Retirement Act for the Public Servants.
And we learned that last year, Legislative Yuan passed a new amendment,
which created impact to the pension system.
And it caused some societal debates.
Therefore, we're waiting for a further version to be provided to us
to see by the Ministry of Personnel to see what the drafts are now.
Are there any other agencies that would like to elaborate on the Division of Residual Property?
If not, then we give the floor back to our reviewers. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Honorable Minister.
I just wanted a little clarification.
You talked about remarrying and alimony,
the conditionality is not being sustained because of remarriage.
Rather than talking about remarriage,
are there considerations within it about child care and child maintenance?
Because often that's where the issue, the problem comes in,
is that the burden of child care post-divorce is not well tidied up.
And then remarrying then becomes a burden on usually the mother or one of the partners
because this is not clearly stated in the alimony clauses or procedures.
Is that clear in your own?
Are there elements of child care that is clear in alimony and dissolution of marriage?
Thank you.
Professor Hisu?
Actually, I was going to ask a similar question because you mentioned about child care included in the alimony.
Alimony is different from child support.
At the time of divorce, the court, if the divorce goes through the court legal procedure,
then the court would say that the father, usually the father,
will pay such and such amount monthly for the child support.
And then some cases, the father doesn't care, even if he was ordered by the court,
maybe a few months he will pay the child support, but afterwards he doesn't pay.
So the former wife has a big problem in raising the child, which is completely different from alimony.
Alimony is the compensation for the time lost by the wife
because of her responsibility taking care of the house in terms of losing opportunity,
all this losing capacity while the husband might, career-wise, continue to develop, etc.
So I think the mixture within the concept of alimony, child care and child support, to me, it's not reasonable.
And then as I talked privately with the bureau chief in the Department of Gender Equality in Korea,
many fathers are just negligent of paying child care support.
And then there is even a website created by men, by the way, saying bad fathers,
and then they are chased and then their identification is exposed, and then out of shame,
then the fathers started to repay the child support.
It's bad fathers, of course, it's a private kind of social punishment.
But anyway, that needs to be settled, whether the dissolution of marriage was settled between the spouses,
okay, we divorce on our own, and then you will pay a certain amount monthly for the child or children that I am in charge of.
Usually mother is given the child care responsibility after the divorce.
That's the reality, which further obstructs her ability to seek employment and then to engage in other activities, etc.
So that would be a question added by the chair's question regarding alimony and child support and remarriage.
So back to you.
Oh, thank you.
Since we have time, I also want to ask something in relation to this alimony
and the cancellation of the alimony in the situation of remarriage.
I mean, if this kind of regulation will, of course, create a strong incentive not to formalize a relationship into marriage,
or are you planning to have a regulation where you also can cancel the alimony in the situation where the lady has moved into a common household with a partner and have a relationship?
So I mean, it is, in a sense, interesting to create mechanisms in the legislation where you, in a sense, put in obstacles for marriage
because usually the society wants people to formalize the relationship.
So I also think that this aspect has to be taken into account.
Thank you.
So back to you.
Delegation, sir.
Thank you.
Obviously, upon remarriage, the issue do back further discussions, and when it comes to alimony, we also need to factor in the child support.
These are two different things.
However, it's possible that there is a need to continue to receive alimony or child support after remarriage,
if that is obstructing them formalizing their relationship because they want to continue receiving the alimony or child support.
Therefore, they would not consider formalizing their new relationship.
So for the Ministry of Justice, would you like to further elaborate?
So this is the Ministry of Justice.
So we would like to further elaborate.
When it comes to child support, like the review committee said, according to civil code that 21116.2,
that the child support would not be canceled upon remarriage, and the elements constituting child support are different from alimony.
Therefore, the remarriage would not cancel child support.
So the former spouse would still need to continue to pay the child support.
And then to answer the next part of the question, would that obstruct the formalization of a new relationship for one of the spouse?
Again, I would like to emphasize, previously we talked about the claim to alimony would be terminated upon remarriage,
but that is the regular alimony paid by installments.
However, it's actually a lump sum payment.
For example, according to the ruling, that would not be affected.
Or they have a pre-negotiation on alimony payment.
That would be not affected.
Of course, one of the parties can evaluate, do they want to have the lump sum of the alimony?
And if they are asking for the regular alimony payment, they need to consider the risks of the cancellation.
Additional information.
So I think we have a follow-up question from IRC about the systematic issue that obstructing formalization of marriage or just co-inhabitation.
According to the draft we have for co-inhabitation, they are not formalizing a spousal relationship.
Therefore, the alimony would not be canceled upon remarriage or entering into a co-habitation relationship.
Thank you, Ministry of Justice, for the answer.
Now we can give time back to the review committee.
We had a very robust conversation.
You still have a question?
Yeah, you have the floor.
Yeah, I asked which countries you took as an example, and you said that Germany and Switzerland.
I think two countries are not universally applicable, so maybe you need to study more if you want to take into account the examples of other countries.
And Germany and Switzerland, they all speak the German part.
Northern Switzerland, they speak German.
So similar social structures.
So maybe you need to take into account a country with different culture, different social structure, et cetera.
Thank you.
Nonetheless, I think we have covered extensively the articles 15 and 16.
And at this point, we would like to sincerely thank all of the government departments, all of the respondents for the insights you've given.
And we would like to adjourn this meeting at this time.
And have a little coffee break.
Thank you.
I'm looking at the agenda from the program.
It appears that our conversation and engagement with the government delegation for the main dialogue and the review of the core document, this is actually the last segment of it.
And so I thought it was appropriate to use this occasion to extend on behalf of the committee our gratitude to the minister, the honorable minister.
Thank you very much for the three words I used, your commitment, your consistency, and your collaboration.
It was very evident in the range of departments and agencies that were present and were able to give insights into all of the intersecting issues and the depth of information that you have provided to us.
Of course, we will be looking at them.
A few suggestions have been coming from the floor.
We are grateful for the things that you already echo in agreement with us.
And we hope that over the next two days, we will go to task and come back to you with some propositions that reflect our mutual conclusions from this conversation.
And on behalf of the review committee, we would like to thank you, honorable minister, and your delegation, and to extend our gratitude to the deputy premier who was here, who took time to be here yesterday, and of course with the support of the wide array of civil society.
Thank you very much for the invitation.
Thank you for the dialogue.
And thank you for the conclusions that you are leading us to arrive at.
We appreciate it.
Have a lovely evening.
Thank you.
We are going to start our another session with the NGOs.
So we'll be back by five minutes after five.
Thank you.
All right everyone, last session of the day, yet another meeting with the NGOs.
Okay, now to begin this session, Madam Chair.
Thank you.
Yes.
So, I would like on behalf of the committee to welcome you to this round of conversation with you, where we appreciate the imputes,
that additional imputes and perspectives from the civil society.
We would be starting from articles 13.
We have 13, 14, 15, and 16.
And so at this point, we would like to open the floor.
But could you please tailor your interventions to article 13 so that we can be focused and
then we can probably for 15 minutes impute from the civil society on article 13.
The floor is open, please.
Please indicate with the result.
Okay, next we will focus on article 13.
For example, same-sex spouses are not legally recognized as the direct linear relatives
of their partner's parents.
And for that reason, they cannot enjoy equal tax benefits such as those regarding land
value tax and house tax for owner-occupied residences in the same manner as heterosexual
marriages.
Tax unfairness is just one dimension of the problem.
The inequalities between same-sex and heterosexual marriages are also manifested in the establishment
of parent-child relationships and access to assisted reproductive technology.
Therefore, we strongly recommend that the legislative review under CEDAW systematically
incorporate a comprehensive assessment of the discriminatory between same-sex marriage
and heterosexual marriage.
Hello, everyone.
I am from the Civil Partnership Rights Alliance.
You talked about gender-friendly toilets.
The government has improvement program in place.
But I would like to emphasize you asked about the gender-inclusive facilities.
Let's take this venue, for example.
Next to our broadcasting station, there is a gender-friendly toilet.
And it used to be a male's toilet, and they just put up a plaque that says gender-friendly
facility.
And nothing was changed inside.
So people go in and become very confused.
They didn't know what's so friendly about this toilet.
So I personally walked in, and there was a male who walked out and looked at me and wondered
if he's in the wrong toilet.
So when the reviewer asked about how we resolve this dispute, we should have a policy that
states clearly what constitutes a gender-friendly toilet.
You can't just put up a plate and say it's gender-friendly, and that makes it gender-friendly.
Next, we are from the Tongzi Hotline.
Following up with the previous statement, yes, currently in terms of gender-friendly
facility in the central government and Ministry of Environment and Ministry of Education and
Ministry of Interior, there are individual guidelines.
A lot of local governments, they have their own guidelines.
But these are encouragements.
There are no mandatory legislations.
So there are a lot of gender-friendly toilets that make it confusing to people.
So we really do need a policy that really sets a standard for gender-friendly facilities.
In Taiwan, we'd like to stress that people with lived experiences should be trained,
recognized, and fairly paid as peer workers, rather than treated only as service recipients
or unpaid peer supporters.
In our experience, women made up a large proportion of peer workers.
And peer work does strengthen their economic independence, rebuild meaningful social roles,
and bring lived experience into expertise for mental health services.
However, not to be recognized as a formal worker and without stable income, these peer
workers face barriers to the financial and banking system, besides the constant denial
of their mental and intellectual capacity to make decisions about their own economic matters.
Additionally, recovery colleges and peer worker programs remain limited overall and
concentrated in urban areas, restricting opportunities for women and gender-diverse
people in rural and remote communities.
We therefore urge the community to recommend a national system for training, employment,
and fair pay, backed by sustainable investment through community mental health services.
Thank you very much.
This is from the Taiwan Equality Campaign.
As mentioned earlier in campuses, the government requires these campuses to set up a certain
number of gender-friendly facilities, but subsidies are not necessarily provided.
These, for example, universities, they are under the jurisdiction of central governments,
but local governments, they usually don't have these budgets.
So these schools, they basically have these female student spaces violated.
They basically just change the plate in front of the toilet and make it gender-friendly.
In Taiwan, a lot of the child-rearing spaces are set up in female toilets, but various
ages and various genders are caretakers, and they need a friendly child-raising space.
This is what the government needs to work on as well.
Six workers, they face irregular income, so they don't have permanent employment or
proof of salary.
So when they are applying for personal loans, mortgage, or credit cards, they are disadvantaged,
and it could lead to structural financial exclusion and insecurity and instability
in terms of housing and financing.
So we hope to refer to the CEDAW Convention allowing sex workers to equally obtain their
credit loans and credit card mortgage and so on without relying on the black market.
The UK government issued in May this year has a guideline to protect, in terms of protecting
the privacy and the dignity, public toilets and hospital wards.
These are unisex spaces.
They can exclude transgenders from entering according to their biological
sex, or we can refer to Japan's experience.
I think we should ask schools to do a survey because a lot of children, they are worried.
For example, girls are afraid to share a space with adult men, and there are parents that
complain that female toilets are turned into male toilets.
And why is it the reverse?
For example, we can see the female toilets usually have a longer line compared to male
toilets, and are they sacrificing parent-friendly toilets and accessible toilets as well in the
process?
Okay, we have two more here.
This is Covenant's watch.
In Taiwan, single parent raising children are usually the male, and they are in economic
disadvantage.
Governments usually provide insufficient care to these families, whether it's divorced family
or family member of incarcerated persons.
They face dual burden of work and family care, and they need to go through certain hurdles
to receive social remedy, even if the government deems that you are eligible for social subsidy.
Unless this adult is taking care of children under the age of six alone, you are considered
making minimal wage.
So they basically give social support allowances to children and elderly instead of adults
at working age, which is a burden to women.
This is the League for Persons with Disabilities.
We see a lot of places that change the plate outside toilets and call it gender-friendly.
They turn accessible toilets into gender-friendly toilets, and we see the same thing in courts as
well.
So we suggest gender-inclusive toilets, but also preserving the accessible toilets so that the
accessible toilets can be preserved for people with real physical disabilities and achieve
equality for public spaces.
This is Awakening Foundation.
Ministry of Labor said that business units employ more than five people.
They must apply labor insurance for the employees, and after 15 years, they can file for pension,
but domestic helpers, they are not eligible.
And mostly, the employers can only keep them in Taiwan for 14 years, so they have a much lower
opportunity to apply for labor insurance pension.
And for them to stay in Taiwan indefinitely, they need to obtain
training, mid-level skills training.
And to receive these trainings, they must be approved by the employees, the employers.
So far, we haven't seen any government reform to protect the lives of these female migrant
workers in their elder years.
Okay, we have four more here.
This is the Garden of Hope Foundation.
Female suffering from domestic violence because of their violent experiences and their
duty of care, they are usually eliminated from the rental housing market.
They don't have a stable place to live, and it will impact their employment and child care
and their mental recovery.
So for these victims of domestic violence, they are facing – it's not just a problem,
I've said, it's a human right.
We have done a survey for these female victims.
They have – 50 percent of them live in places that are very small for two people,
or including children.
So a lot of female victims of domestic violence, after they leave home, they face
unfriendly rental market.
So I think this should be taken into consideration of our policy to really provide a suitable
environment for them to support their recovery and their child raising.
We have another one here.
This is the Child Mothers Shield Alliance.
In the previous session, they talked about care economy, and we can see the government
hasn't really provided a comprehensive explanation of this.
I think Taiwan faces an intersectional crisis of lower birth rate and aging society.
We don't see the unpaid care that is a service provided every day in the household.
We are lower – we are underestimating the social support cost, and I hope that unpaid
care can be included in the consideration of social cost and be counted towards our
GDP because of this unseen work that supports the growth of children and the care of elders
and the stability of the families.
And that's the duty of the mothers.
It's not just the personal service provided in the household, but what supports the society.
Parents and Children's Protection Association, first time making comments.
So all these so-called gender inclusive spaces, these privacy protection spaces for women,
have you actually asked little girls how do they feel?
So my child is only 12 years old, but nobody asks about their feelings.
Are you treating them in a friendly way when you make the arrangement for these gender
inclusive spaces?
Are you factor in the feelings of little girls?
Thank you.
Alliance for Women's Rights and Sustainable Development.
To answer Marion's question before, you actually asked about the taxation regime.
Are they adopting appropriate measures to be – to also do this GIA, especially this
evaluation of intersectionality?
And then according to Article 13 of CEDAW, the gender equality and tax policy,
we can actually see on the institutional side and also the practical side.
Institutionally speaking, we do have these regimes, the different acts and the regulations,
and also the new taxation regimes need to go through GIA.
However, the taxation itself do not have these intersectionality assessment,
just like you mentioned, that the intersectionality evaluation and assessment,
especially the so-called gender tax assessment is missing.
And also intersectionality assessment also fail to pay attention to single parents,
people living with disabilities, indigenous women and rural women,
and also female entrepreneurs.
Do they enjoy the benefits of tax?
Last one, Taiwan Disabled Women Alliance for Equal Rights.
And then for these flying goals program mentioned by MOEA, there are no statistics
for women with disabilities.
Are they eligible?
Did they apply for that program?
And also for people with disabilities, when they apply for loan and for entrepreneurship,
there are no data whatsoever.
We ask the government to have the statistics.
And also, female with disabilities, it's really difficult for them to live independently
because there are no job opportunities and also a lot of these subsidies only offer
on the basis of households and a factor in household income.
Therefore, women with disabilities are excluded from these allowances and benefits,
are further exacerbating their difficulties.
Therefore, we will recommend the Taiwan Social Relief Act should stop
from making these relief on the basis of households.
Yeah, Madam Chair, that's it for Article 13.
Thank you very much, Xie Xie.
We will now move on to Article 14.
I think we got quite a breadth of imputes.
We appreciate it.
But we would like to know if there are considerations, perspectives from civil society.
And of course, I would request that we give preference to those who have not spoken.
So for the first set, and then we can take from others later.
Thank you.
So Article 14, anyone would like to go first?
For those who hasn't spoken yet, yeah, the back rolls over here.
This is New Vitality Independent Living Association.
Even though the government promotes gender-inclusive facilities,
and also we have policies to empower women economically.
However, they are not sufficiently addressing the needs of people with intersectionality
in areas of gender, disability, age, and immigrant identity.
Therefore, the current practice in building gender-inclusive facilities
miss an overarching, consistent regulation and monitoring mechanism.
And in workspace, on campus, in public space, they fail to factor in the needs of people
of diverse genders, and also the accessibility for people with disabilities.
And also, long-term care, personal assistance,
and daycare and community-based services are also far from enough.
And most of the care responsibilities are still shouldered by women,
and that is also obstructing their opportunities in seeking employment,
having additional income, and retirement protection.
And then because these women, their opportunity for career development is limited,
and also they are denied access to education.
They are even more possible to be trapped by poverty.
And a lot of disabled women, they are also shouldering family care responsibilities.
And these unpaid labor for a long time has been neglected by the system and institution,
and also family care in Taiwan highly depend on immigrant foreign workers.
However, they are not receiving enough labor condition protection and social protection.
We urge the government to establish
gender-inclusive overarching standards for accessible spaces,
and there should be a unilateral, unified standards and monitoring mechanisms.
And also, they should expand the resources available for care and personal assistance.
And also, there should be a system that protects the care workers
and give them protection of pension after retirement.
We should recognize the values of unpaid labor and enhance these
measures to lift disabled women out of poverty.
And we should also have a comprehensive protection for workers.
Thank you very much.
And then any other NGO representative would like to speak on Article 14.
Women Rescue Foundation.
This afternoon, when we talk about rural women,
according to the report, we fail to – we cannot really see the medical access issue
for rural women in practice.
Many of the rural villages in Taiwan faces severe aging issues,
and then they are – they don't have easy access to medical care.
And then when it comes to the transportation, subsidiaries are quite low.
Therefore, rural women, if they want to seek health care support,
it's difficult for them to find medical resources.
Therefore, we would like to urge the government to give sufficient funding
to support the transportation for these rural women when they need to seek medical attention.
So in that way, we can facilitate the convenience for them to seek medical help.
Any other representative would like to speak on Article 14?
Please.
So according to the statistics of Ministry of Labor, we can actually see that
households with higher income, they have lower percentage of asking for parental leave
because our parental leave is tied with the tiered insurance labor.
So even though the paid parental leave, especially for those high-income households,
well, it's not a good benefit.
And also in Japan, in Korea, they have these parental leave for both parents.
And then also in the first few months, the allowance will be 100 percent of paid leave.
It's the same in Japan.
But in Taiwan, we only compensate up to 80 percent of salary,
and then that period is only six months to maximum.
However, in Korea and Japan, they can have that benefit up to 12 months.
That is why a lot of Taiwanese laborers will not enjoy the benefits
of parental leave because of economic reasons.
For Article 14.
Madam Chair, that's what we have for Article 14.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I think Article 15 is a very short article.
And so we had just one question to the delegation.
What we would like to open to civil society if they have any additional imputes.
Article 15.
On Article 15.
Thank you.
Any comments for Article 15?
So the first time making comments, the Life Equality Rights Association,
I am actually supporting the victim, family, families of victims.
So we are all equal in front of law.
I would like to cite one judge from New Taipei City.
If you are actually, I think, an eye for an eye, we can, that is definitely granted.
Therefore, this is what a point I would like to make.
We are all equal in front of the law.
And we have 2,000 judges around Taiwan.
Female judges account for 52 percent.
And prosecutors, we have 1,237 for them.
And we would like to ask you to actually stand up and then actually say no to the bullying.
And I would also like to ask the covenants watch.
Where is your conscience?
I know you don't have conscience because you have been supporting the perpetrators.
And you are scattering salt on the wounds of the victims and the victims' families.
And you are bullying them psychologically.
Article 15, anyone?
This is Taiwan Sex Industry Workers' Rights Association.
With regard to Article 15, we have been repeatedly mentioned that sex workers,
they are in economic poverty.
And then they don't have accessibility to judicial resources.
And also, like the national report said, that it seems the Social Order Maintaining Act,
it's not neutral because it's actually treating different parties differently in the results.
So we would like to urge the committee to pay attention to that.
Anyone who hasn't spoken yet, would you like to speak on Article 15?
So this is Taiwan League of Persons with Disabilities.
So just like I mentioned before, Ministry of Health has already incorporated into draft
for People with Disabilities Protection Act the reasonable accommodation,
even though it's already added into the new draft.
However, the definition is incomplete.
For example, there is a very small scope of reasonable accommodation.
It's not extending to daily lives.
And also, the reasonable accommodation only reflects on negotiation process.
But we should do more beyond that.
We want to see the reasonable accommodation is actually made so we can really enjoy equal
treatment.
And also, according to the covenants, which has already been adopted for 12 years,
however, in Disability Protection Act, they are saying that the reasonable accommodation
would only become effective two years later.
So we actually see a very huge gap and divide between our ideal timetable and that of the
government.
So in addition to the worship guilds, we also have this very severe situation
of patriarchal feature and characteristics in the household registration system.
So for each of the newborn, that you can actually see the eldest son, eldest daughter,
second son, and second daughter.
And you can actually see if this mother of the child is not in marriage relationship,
then it's just one child.
However, when there is a man involved, then it becomes the man's first child or second
child.
So it's a very patriarchal-oriented system.
Because for the same-sex marriage, we don't have that patriarchal characteristics.
And therefore, for any child who is born in a same-sex marriage relationship,
then there would be no marker of firstborn and secondborn.
So we would like to urge the community to also pay attention to this issue.
Thank you very much.
And now we move on to the last article, which is Article 16 on family life.
And we would now like to open the floor for imputes from civil society.
Thank you.
We are Taiwan non-binary queer sluts.
All of the data in the national reports are still limited to the binary gender system.
We implore the government to include non-binary individuals in its statistics so that they are
no longer left out of official figures.
We emphasize that the court's position that legal gender market change without compulsory
surgery is not a settled legal principle.
However, there are still judges who object to applicants' claims.
We urge the Ministry of the Interior and the Legislature Yuan to address this situation,
which violates human rights of trans people.
According to point 16 of the document, everyone, even those with an unknown gender designation
on their birth certificate, must be registered in a household registry as male or female.
And ID numbers are assigned according to the binary gender system.
Anyone who seizes a national ID number can know a person's legal gender without seeing
the gender marker, causing significant harm to non-binary individuals.
This must be rectified immediately.
Thank you.
Regarding domestic violence mediation that is inappropriate, it's not resolved, and
there is still the visitation and alimony issues regarding the dissolution upon
the divorce or remarriage, and there is also the revoke of protection orders.
And third, we can see that currently the mediation rights are not fully informed.
The plaintiffs are not currently fully informed.
There is a differential of regulations violating the rights of children of same-sex marriages
because adoption takes six months to one year.
Newborns are taking the most time to take care of them, and it's very difficult for them to go into
this care period, and it's a time when there are more conflicts between the spouses.
So if the adoption is not, for example, if the spouses are, the couples are indigenous persons,
and without the adoption process completed, they cannot choose, the person who did not bear the
child cannot choose for the child to become, to take up, adopt indigenous status.
So right now it's in, it does not benefit the children's rights and protection.
This is the awakening foundation regarding divorce.
The current division of pensions, we ask that the 1030 Civil Code should just include the division
of pensions and whether or not alimony can be disilluded upon remarriage.
We think it's a punishment for remarriage.
We know that the alimony cannot be paid for life, so it's unreasonable for it to cancel alimony upon remarriage.
And also, some of the plaintiffs, they don't really know the rights of their request,
and they're not properly cared for in terms of the security during the mediation,
even though it's confirmed by the judge in practice.
The judge will say, if you don't accept my ruling, I won't rule for a divorce.
So a lot of the times the judges force the disadvantaged person to accept the ruling.
Regarding the residual property division, we know that pension is included in the residual property,
but in reality, a lot of people are divorced before retirement,
so they are unable to request the pension.
And from 2020 to date, we are still waiting for a draft to be adopted.
So when you worry about the 10-year that it will take, it's not coming out of thin air.
It's a real worry.
And we know that the protection gaps for these disadvantaged spouses are facing vulnerability.
Right now, we strongly object alimony attached to remarriage,
and we think it's very important that we need to have a package.
According to the constitutional ruling number four in 2023,
we can see it's very easy for them to have a divorce for request for alimony.
And right now, according to the current clause, it's impossible for people to request alimony.
So we hope that you can conclude in your concluding opinion to request this.
I am a commissioner of the Gender Equality Commission.
Right now, the other spouse of the civil servant or teacher,
you need to be reciprocal in requiring the pension be divided.
So if during the divorce, they still have a job, they don't have the right to ask for the pension.
And the administrative court and the domestic affairs court have differences in their rulings,
determining the contributions to the marriage.
It's impossible for the state to include everything that's related to the labor insurance.
If you have a job, you have the status of a labor,
you cannot request the pension of your other half.
And if you are asking for alimony, a lot of the times it's a full package.
So you think you're asking for alimony, but you're asking for child support or the other way around,
and we need to differentiate this.
And I would like to respond that if, in fact, you're cohabiting or you are getting a divorce
or getting a remarriage, we should at least have a certificate of remarriage
to make sure that you really are remarried.
But a lot of the times, if it's a reimbursive alimony,
sometimes it cannot be paid in one installment.
And when it's canceled during the remarriage, it will cancel the nature of the reimbursement.
Are there anyone who hasn't spoken regarding Article 16?
Regarding Article 16, the domestic violence in marriage,
the government responded to Article 16.
But the real issue is, are the women really safe?
We have helped a lot of the women who faced domestic violence.
They're facing a lot of re-offenses and the re-traumatization of the entire process.
The government has no evidence that the re-offense of domestic violence rate is lowering,
and there is no proof to say that once sexual harassment report is made,
the women won't be harmed again.
And for example, the Kaohsiung case and the various cases in Chuchen, in New Taipei City,
and in Hsinchu, what has the National Human Rights Commission done for these women?
They are just preferring the perpetrators and not helping the victims.
Chair?
Thank you very much.
I don't see any other flags up or indication to take the floor.
And so I would like to, at this point, sincerely thank the civil society community.
I think your imputes, you have helped to clarify a number of issues,
to sharpen our understanding of the reality.
And there are new dimensions to the issues that you have brought to the table.
The issue of household registration was one that I noted.
Binary data, that's largely what is there.
And I'm sure there's always room for improving data collection to guide policy.
So that's it for today.
Thank you very much to all the members of the International Review Committee.
And of course, we thank you, to all of you, our NGO partners here for your participation.
Thank you.
That's it for today.
Have a great evening, everybody.
Thank you.
Any additional information that you would like to add, please send it to the committee.
And please send it to my email.
Any questions?
No questions.